<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A practical discourse concerning the choice benefit of communion with God in his house witnessed unto by the experience of saints as the best improvement of time : being the summe of several sermons on Psal. 84. 10 preach'd in Boston on lecture-dayes / by Joshua Moody.</title>
            <author>Moodey, Joshua, 1633?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W479532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07953296</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07953296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40711</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40711)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1210:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A practical discourse concerning the choice benefit of communion with God in his house witnessed unto by the experience of saints as the best improvement of time : being the summe of several sermons on Psal. 84. 10 preach'd in Boston on lecture-dayes / by Joshua Moody.</title>
                  <author>Moodey, Joshua, 1633?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 109 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Pierce for Joseph Brunning,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston in New-England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXIV, 10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, American --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:1"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>THere are Literal faults and miſpointings which if the Reader's Curioſity obſerves it is hoped his Candour will pardon. Such as are moſt material may be thus amended,</p>
            <p>PAge 28. Line 4. for <hi>theſe</hi> read they. p. 29. l. 10. dele and. p. 31. l. 17. for <hi>Breath</hi> r. Breaſt. p. 32. l. 17. for <hi>&amp; food ſo</hi> r. food, and ſo. p. 36. l. 6. for <hi>Bonds</hi> r. Bands. p. 82. l. 3. for <hi>Denunciation</hi> r. Denomination. p. 95. l. ult. and penult. dele the Tautology. p. 96. l. 11. dele about. p. 100. l. ult. r. Look for. p. 109. l. 20. dele At.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A PRACTICAL</hi> DISCOURSE CONCERNING <hi>THE</hi> CHOICE BENEFIT of <hi>Communion</hi> with <hi>GOD</hi> in His HOUSE, Witneſſed unto by the Experience of Saints as <hi>The beſt Improvement of TIME.</hi> Being the Summe of ſeveral Sermons on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 10.</p>
            <p>Preach'd in <hi>Boſton</hi> on <hi>Lecture-Dayes</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JOSHUA MOODY <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4.</bibl> 
               <hi>One thing</hi> have I deſired of the Lord, that I will ſeek after, that I may dwell in the <hi>Houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Lord</hi> all the days of my life &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </bibl> To ſee thy power and thy glory ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thee in the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ON</hi> IN <hi>NEW-ENGLAND</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Pierce</hi> for <hi>Joſeph Brunning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> And are to be ſold at his Shop at the Corner of <hi>Priſon-Lane</hi> next the <hi>Exchange.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Enſuing <hi>Sermons</hi> are ſuch for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Uſefulneſs</hi> of them that they will ſufficiently commend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>judicious:</hi> It being of great and univerſal Concern to Rational and Intelligent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be directed and helped in <hi>Improvement</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> to the <hi>beſt Advantage.</hi> The Labours of the Reverend <hi>Authour</hi> for the Clearing and Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>this</hi> in the following <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> upon that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> no <hi>Letters</hi> of <hi>Commendation;</hi> He did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Commend himſelf to the Conſciences <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Preaching</hi> of them, of whom I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelf one, and ſuch an one who is ſenſible that his <hi>Candle-light</hi> will not further, nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute any thing to the Clear and powerful De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations and Evidences, you will find in the
<pb facs="tcp:40711:3"/>
ſerious Peruſal of them. Yet being deſired to ſay ſomething, I was willing to teſtifie my Eſteem of its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs and <hi>Seaſonableneſs</hi> to our preſent Time, which not only commends <hi>things</hi> to us for our delightful <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>Eccleſ. 3. 10.</hi> by the wiſe over-ruling Providence of God, but <hi>Inſtruments</hi> tho, as fitted for <hi>Miniſterial work</hi> Iſa. 50. 4.</p>
            <p>The great Evil that is moſt provoking to God among a <hi>profeſſing People</hi> (eſpecially <hi>ſincere Chriſtians</hi>) even the root-evil whence all other do iſſue is that which Chriſt charges upon the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> Rev. 2. 5. <hi>the want of firſt-Love.</hi> Tho' true Converts have not a defect of a principle of Love, which may diſtinguiſh them from the moſt ſpecious <hi>Hypocrites;</hi> yet may not be ſo warm and fervent as in their firſt union to Chriſt, and Communion with God in their Pardon and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This is more offenſive to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in true Saints than the open out-breakings of thoſe that are profane ſinners, and for which he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens <hi>Removing the Candleſtick</hi> if his Warning and Advice be not attended.</p>
            <p>What can be more ſuitable then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe Tendency is to further us in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with the mind of Chriſt to ſuch a people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and our condition is ſo like, <hi>non ovum ovo ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</hi> As,</p>
            <p>1. To put us in mind <hi>whence we are fallen.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40711:3"/>
It is Communion with God in his <hi>Ordinances</hi> that makes Time there ſo valuable above all other <hi>1. Pet. 3. 8.</hi> This <hi>one thing</hi> is <hi>that</hi> the Apoſtle would not have us ignorant of viz. that <hi>one day with God is as a Thouſand years, &amp; a 1000 years as one day:</hi> It is true there he Speaks of God's Eternity which is not meaſured by Time, nor is any Time conſiderable with it; yet it may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved with reſpect to Believers being with God, here is ſuch an immenſe and univerſal good that we have more true ſoul-pleaſure with God himſelf in an <hi>Hour,</hi> than if we had the quinteſſence of Created Good <hi>all our Dayes,</hi> therein we are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy, it is our <hi>Heaven upon Earth.</hi> But if theſe be Ordinary dayes and under common Eſteem with us, that we go not to his Houſe to enjoy God as our <hi>Exceeding Joy,</hi> we have loſt our Communion with God (and ſo far our Happineſs) that we are herein like <hi>other</hi> men.</p>
            <p>2. If this were practically remembered, it might have its Influence to promove our Repentance in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing thoſe ſins and that bitterly that have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Beloved</hi> to with-draw. It is not that Ordinances are not as precious in <hi>themſelves</hi> as they have been to us and other Saints, nor is it that they are not as ſuitable meanes to convey thoſe Bleſſings, nor is it want of kindneſs and love in God and Jeſus Chriſt who have the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb facs="tcp:40711:4"/>
               <hi>in</hi> and deſire <hi>of</hi> Communion with Believers; and the deſign of his Grace <hi>in</hi> us, and his Ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances <hi>to</hi> us is that he might enjoy us, but our carnally-ſecure Hearts in with-drawing from him have provoked him to with-draw from us <hi>Cant. 5. 2,—6.</hi> It began in our low eſteem of Chriſt &amp; his Fellowſhip, bemoan it heartily and labour to recover it.</p>
            <p>If this be alſo attended with ſuitable <hi>Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi> in a diligent Frequenting the <hi>HOUSE</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and preſſing after Fellowſhip with the Father and the Son (the great deſign of Ordinances) and that we will not be ſatisfied without Him, then ſhall we again have our <hi>beſt dayes</hi> returned to us. All theſe may be furthered by our diligent Peruſal of the <hi>Sermons here preſented us,</hi> that ſhew what the benefit is that Saints do experience in Ordinances ſo improved.</p>
            <p>That it may be accompanied to thee in <hi>reading</hi> with the gracious preſence of the Holy Spirit that breathed in its <hi>Delivery,</hi> for ends fore mentioned, that ſo the joy of <hi>his</hi> Salvation may be reſtored, and <hi>Houſe of God</hi> continued to us, is my earneſt Prayer, to which I deſire thy AMEN, who am thy ſoul's well-wiſher</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JAMES ALLEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40711:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 84. 10.</bibl>
               <q>For a day in thy Courts is better than a Thouſand:—</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AFter the many Anxious Enquiries and Debates about the <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> or <hi>Chiefeſt Good</hi> of the rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in more Ancient and darker Times; It hath been at length, by Him that brought Life and Immortality to light, clearly evinced, and among Chriſtians put beyond diſpute, that <hi>This is life eternal to know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent. Joh.</hi> 17. 3. Hence in all Ages thoſe with whom this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine hath effectually obtained, have held them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged highly to prize, and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, conſtantly and carefully to attend upon all thoſe waies that have been recommended to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40711:5"/>
them by the Stamp of Divine Inſtitution, as meanes of growing in the knowledge <hi>of,</hi> or get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, maintaining, and encreaſing their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion <hi>with</hi> this God in Chriſt, whom they do value as their Happineſs. And for this very reaſon it is that all pious ſouls have ever had ſo venerable an Eſteem of the Houſe of God, and the Ordinances or Inſtituted Worſhip thereof, as wayes and Meanes appointed unto the End propoſed: which by their Encomiums <hi>of,</hi> Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs <hi>in,</hi> and Thankfulneſs <hi>for</hi> while they have had the liberty of enjoying the ſame, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with vehement Pantings, and inſatiable Longings-after (when bereaved of them) they have plentifully diſcovered. Inſomuch that true Love, and hearty unfeigned Devotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Houſe of God has been look'd at as a Mark of Sincerity where it hath been found. Thus <hi>David</hi> when making his appeal to God about his Integrity <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26. 8. brings this for one Argument, viz. his <hi>Love to the habitation of His Houſe, and place where his Honour dwells.</hi> And on the other hand the decay of love to God's Houſe appearing either in a total neglect thereof, or Slightineſs and Indifferency there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, among the Profeſſors of Religion hath been accounted a ſad Symptome of the decay of the power of Godlineſs, a ſign of great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy, and an Introduction of Apoſtacy; as alſo an awful Prognoſtick of great Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40711:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
if not ruinatin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amity haſtning on ſuch a People. This of the moſt bitter provocations of the Lord's Sons and Daughters when they have loſt their Affection to their Fathers houſe, and either care not to come there or if they do, it is with ſuch cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, formality and Slightineſs, and with ſo little heart and hungring after Fellowſhip with Himſelf there, that he accounts himſelf rather Mock'd than honour'd by ſuch Spiritleſs and Truthleſs Performances. this kindles ſuch a fire in his Anger that nothing but the bloud of Chriſt in a way of unfeigned Repentance and Reformation can put out.</p>
            <p>If I miſtake not in mine Obſervation there ſeems to be a great falling ſhort in that Love and Zeal for the Worſhip of God, and that Labour and Frequency of waiting upon Him in his Houſe, both on Sabbath dayes and Lecture dayes, that hath been formerly obſerved in thoſe that have profeſſed Chriſtianlty in Truth-Men do not make ſo great, or Momentous and Neceſſary a buſineſs thereof, as heretofore. A dangerous condition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> both as it intimates a Decay in the very Vitals of Religion, and as it makes way for God's Anger to come upon ſuch a degenerate Generation.</p>
            <p>Our Fathers have told us how precious the Word of God was in their dayes, and proved their high Eſteem thereof by the paines they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40711:6"/>
were wont to take in travelling many a mile to a Sermon in there own Land; as alſo by their Leaving <hi>All</hi> to follow the Lord ſome Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Miles into a Wilderneſs, that they might freely Enjoy the liberties of his Houſe, and obtain Communion with Him there.</p>
            <p>With what an ill face then it does look, that we ſhould flagg in our Affections <hi>to,</hi> and grow Cold in our Attendance <hi>on</hi> thoſe high and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable enjoyments that our Fathers purchaſed at ſo dear a Rate, I leave to the ſad and ſerious Conſideration of all thinking Chriſtians. Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry proffitable Lectures round about us quite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid down! And ſome who keep up Lectures (eſpecially in Country-Towns, where the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of a Market and other ſecular Buſineſs do not induce People to afford their Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) are ready to think whether they were not better lay them down alſo than preach to bare walls, or at leaſt to ſuch thinn Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</p>
            <p>My Aym in chooſing <hi>this Text,</hi> at <hi>this Time,</hi> and in <hi>this Place</hi> of general Reſort is to bear my Teſtimony againſt this growing and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Evil, and to endeavour the reviveing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>firſt Love</hi> and ancient Affection to the <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> of God, as not knowing where in I may do better ſervice for our God, and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the People of our God, than by raiſing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>God</hi> among us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40711:6"/>And the words read furniſh me with a ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Medium</hi> unto ſuch an end, taken from the Topick of Gain and Profit that will redound unto the behoof of them that are ſerious there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. An Argument which if it be Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively urged, and God ſhall pleaſe to <hi>ſet in</hi> therewith, we ſhall not need doubt of ſome good Succeſs. Gain ſmells ſweet in moſt mens Noſtrils. He that baits his hook with Profit, may expect not to toyl in vain, provided it be underſtood and realized. So ſweet and allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſound does Gain make, that he who can <hi>harp well upon</hi> that <hi>ſtring</hi> may hope for an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive Auditory. Therefore doth the Lord bait the net of his Goſpel which he lets down in his Houſe with a promiſe of a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward unto all that ſhall be drawn thereinto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>g Would men be convinced that there is no way of ſpending Time ſo much to advantage as in the Houſe of God, it is to be hoped that the end would be anſwered. When matter of Gain was diſcourſed by <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the Craftsmen on the one hand, and Danger of Loſing their Religion (tho' indeed it was no Religion) on the other hand (<hi>Act.</hi> 19. 34.) it drew the whole City together, and made them continue for two houres ſpace in one conſtant Cry to proclaim their Devotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> Mee-thinks the greater Gain to be gotten by waiting on God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40711:7"/>
in his Houſe, with the danger of loſing our Religion (which by the neglect of that duty is eminently endangered,) ſhould have a greater Influence, and oblige us to attendance, and that with all Seriouſneſs and Joyfulneſs. Why ſhould not the whole City come together, and ſpend the two hours allotted for this Exerciſe in the Worſhip of the true God, with as great readineſs and as little wearineſs as they did in the ſervice of an Idol?</p>
            <p>There needs not much to be ſaid to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text in order to the clearing of the Text. Brieſly, the Pſalm ſeems plainly to have a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to ſome Time wherein the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> was deprived of the Liberties of Gods Houſe, which he looks at as a ſore Affliction, and does very Pathetically and feelingly bewail the ſame, adding vehement Soul-longings, even unto fainting, with reiterated and ſundry wayes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced Supplications that he might be repoſſeſs'd of thoſe (at preſent loſt) Priviledges.</p>
            <p>Take the Text as related to the Context and it Contains one Reaſon of the above-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Longings and Cryings after the Houſe of God, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe he ſaw it to be a place far more for his advantage to dwell in, it was by many degrees better being there than elſwhere. And there to be where it is beſt to be, ſhould be every mans deſire.</p>
            <p>Take the words ſeperatly conſidered in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40711:7"/>
and they are a compariſon between a Day ſpent in the Courts of God's Houſe, and elſwhere; and the preference is given to a day there, and that by the difference of a Thouſand to One.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Day in thy Courts is better than a Thouſand,</hi>] Or it may be read <hi>A Day is</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood <hi>in thy Courts above a Thouſand.</hi> The Comparative degree [<hi>better</hi>] being ſo rendered <hi>good before.</hi> Or I know not why it may not be as well read [<hi>A good day in thy Courts is before a Thouſand.</hi>] The Houſe of God is a good place, and all our dayes <hi>there</hi> are good daies in themſelves, and its our own fault if they be not ſo to us.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not Criticiſe upon it, the ſenſe comes all to one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A day</hi>] and by like reaſon a <hi>part</hi> of a day when we ſpend not the whole day there; there being no Neceſſity of taking [<hi>Day</hi>] here for a day in propriety of ſpeech, either natural or Artificial: But it may intend any part or por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Time, leſs or more that is appointed for that Imployment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In thy Courts</hi>] A Court is a place or ſpace of Ground, more peculiarly impropriated and belonging to the uſe of an Houſe, ſequeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed or diſtinguiſhed from that which lies in Common, and through which we have admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the Houſe. Take it as referring and belonging to the <hi>Temple,</hi> and then it intends
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40711:8"/>
that place adjoyning to the ſame, into which the people might come to worſhip God, and to hear his Word read and expounded, and ſo the Court by a <hi>Metonymie</hi> may be put for the Worſhip there performed, and the Fellowſhip with God there obtained. So that when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeaks of his <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tings for God's Courts,</hi> and his <hi>longings to be there,</hi> he intends to intimate his great Affection <hi>for,</hi> and deſire <hi>after</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing near to God in the Publique Inſtituted Worſhip of his Houſe, from which he was now baniſhed. And as their Temple Worſhip was a Type of our <hi>Goſpel Worſhip;</hi> So to us it may ſignifie (and we may improve the whole Pſalm to teach us) the worth and glory of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in his Houſe, how it is to be value<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or eſteemed by us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Better than a Thouſand] i. e.</hi> abundantly better, many degrees better, a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber being put here for an Uncertain, and it is to ſhew that there is a Vaſt and Inexpreſſible Difference between them, and that the Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is by many degrees to be given to the Houſe of God: and that there is no Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon between ſpending of time there and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. He inſtanceth in a Thouſand, and yet tells us that does not reach it, for <hi>one day</hi> there <hi>is beter than a Thouſand,</hi> and if you ſhould Add a Thouſand more, it would ſtill hold true.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40711:8"/>The Words then contain this Doctrinal Concluſion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That it is an exceeding profitable way of ſpending Time, to ſpend it in the Publique Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in his Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The beſt way by a Thouſand to one of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving Time, is to Improve it in the way of Publique Inſtituted worſhip. There is more than a Thouſand to one difference between Time ſpent in God's Houſe, and ſpent any where elſe. Excellent is the advantage that we may make of Time by uſing it in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip of God, above any other way imaginable.</p>
            <p>Time is one of the rareſt Jewels and moſt precious Talents, with which the Lord is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting us in this World, our Felicity both here and hereafter depending upon the <hi>well-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving</hi> of it, and man's Miſery ariſing from hence, becauſe he does not know his Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Then of excellent uſe muſt this Truth needs be, which tells us how to <hi>huſband our Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ter</hi> the beſt manner, ſo as to make it turn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to account. They that have but little Time had need enquire how they ſhall doe to make the moſt of it, why the <hi>Doctrine</hi> directs in that great Enquiry, Spend as much of it as you can in the Houſe of God, Viſit God at his Houſe as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40711:9"/>
o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as you may, Loſe no opportunity of being with God <hi>there;</hi> Nothing will be ſo beneficial to you as your ſo doing.</p>
            <p>And the Doctrine ſpeaks of Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in God's Houſe, for it is that which the Text and Context intend.</p>
            <p>For the proof of this Aſſertion, there needs the leſs to be ſaid, becauſe it is ſo plainly and poſitively affirmed in the Text, being Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to our belief not only by the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>David,</hi> (a man ſo able to judge of the worth of a day in God's Houſe, unto which both by the Enjoyment and Want thereof he had been advantaged,) but alſo coming to us with the <hi>ſtamp</hi> of Divine Authority upon it. The Spirit of God in <hi>David</hi> gives this Price of a <hi>Day in Gods Houſe,</hi> and therefore we may take it ſo, and be aſſured it is not overprized.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe it is ſo little practically believed it may not be amiſs to ſpend ſome Time in the Demonſtrating thereof.</p>
            <p>Now the Text ſaith that <hi>a day ſpent in the Houſe of God, is better than a Thouſand dayes,</hi> it doth not ſay <hi>where,</hi> or <hi>how ſpent,</hi> but leaves it indefinitely, and may be underſtood of ſo many dayes ſpent any where elſe that we may imagine; and we ſhall find that Time ſpent in the Houſe of God is better than any other where.</p>
            <p>We may therefore illuſtrate and prove this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40711:9"/>
Truth by conſidering the various wayes of Spending Time, and comparing the advantage gained by being in the Houſe of God, above what is to be gotten otherwhere, the difference will appear, and the Preference be found where the Doctrine places it.</p>
            <p>Time is ſpent either in Idleneſs or Action, in doing <hi>Nothing</hi> (if at leaſt it be poſſible for a man at any time not to doe ſomething, as in a ſenſe it is) or <hi>Something.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Then, <hi>To ſpend Time in the Houſe of God is a Thouſand times better than to ſpend it in Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> For of Idleneſs comes no goodneſs. <hi>In all Labour there is profit, but the talk of the lips tendeth only to Poverty. Prov.</hi> 14. 23. And I fear many an hour that ſhould be ſpent in God's Houſe is ſpent ſo. He that is doing nothing, is getting nothing; for <hi>of nothing comes nothing.</hi> If Conſcience tell thee thou haſt been ſtanding Idle in the Market place, or doing nothing in thine own houſe or elſe-where, thou hadſt a Thouſand times better been at a Sermon, for there thou might'ſt have done &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tten ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing. A day in the Houſe of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand times better than doing (and ſo get<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>) nothing, there being no Compariſon between ſomething and nothing. Tho alſo it is worſe than ſo, becauſe it is a ſin to be Idle, Yea and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>moſt pernicious and ruinating evil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40711:10"/>
which expoſes men to Tentation, and is the occaſion of any thing that is ſinful. <hi>Idleneſs was one of the ſins of Sodom</hi> (Ezek. 16. 49.)</p>
            <p>2 <hi>If men are doing ſomething and not utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly idle, yet if not well employed, it's a Thouſand times better to be in the Houſe of God.</hi> They may not be Sleeping, Idleing, Sitting ſtill, but very buſie, and yet if not a doing good, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the dreadful wages that will ſurely be paid to ſuch in the iſſue, will plentifully evince this Truth. Every ſinner ſhall one day <hi>ſay, I have ſinned and perverted that which was right, and it profited me not. Job.</hi> 33. 27. Sin may be ſweet in the committing, but bitterneſs in the end. <hi>Stollen waters are ſweet,—but—the dead are there. (Prov. 9. ult.)</hi> Is not much of that Time which is by ſome ſpent in the Houſe of God to their great Advantage, by others elſe-where miſpent in Drinking, Carrouſing, Gameing, in Riotting and Drunkenneſs, in Chambering and Wantonneſs? And what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit will you find in theſe things when your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>unt comes to be made up? The Apoſtle makes that Appeal to them after they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened and ſanctified, (and ſo beſt able to judge <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 20, 21.) <hi>What fruit had yee while ſervants of Sin?</hi> what wages for your ſervice? Shame and Death being the end of thoſe waies: Then you had a Thouſand times
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40711:10"/>
better been in the Houſe of God, ſeeking Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Life.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Time ſpent in God's Houſe is better t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſpent about any ſecular Buſineſs or Worldly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns.</hi> It's Lawful, yea a Duty to be diligent in your particular Callings, God hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us in the ſweat of our brows to get our Bread, and enjoyned us ſix dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and doe all that we have to doe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hath promiſed us if we acknowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our waies, to direct our pathes, to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s whitherſoever we turn our ſelves, to bleſs our Labour in the Houſe and Field &amp;c. In all this our Labour there is Profit, but yet no ſuch Profit or gain as is to be had in the Houſe of God. Let men be in their Fields, Gardens, Orchards, in their Shops &amp; Ware-houſes, let them be Labouring, Merchandizing there, and have never ſo many advantages before them to get by their Commodities, let them buy and ſell and get gain, and as much gain as they would propoſe to themſelves, or could wiſh; yet ſtill one day in God's Houſe is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a Thouſand thus improved. God gives greater wages for working in his Houſe than can be gotten with all our paine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Contrivance in our own. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arms and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize interfere with your Call of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, if worldly Cares and Buſineſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Thorns to Choak the Word, to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aden your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40711:11"/>
Affections thereto, draw away your Spirits therefrom, and hinder your fruitfulneſs under the ſame; they are to be lookt upon as Snares and Traps and Cheaters, and to be treated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: But uſe theſe things how you will, with never ſo much Care and Circumſpection, ſtill your Time in the Houſe of God will be found your beſt Time.</p>
            <p>4. I may add, that <hi>Time is better ſpent in God's Houſe, than in Religious duties in a private way; Nor can one ſpend that Time</hi> lawfully, <hi>much leſs</hi> profitably <hi>in private devotions, which is appointed for publick Worſhip, if God gives him an opportunity of enjoying it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Going to the Houſe of God with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that keep Holy day, is far more eligible &amp; profitable than tarrying at home tho' a man ſhould read a better Sermon in his own Houſe than he may hear in God's Houſe. Doubtleſs <hi>David</hi> had his waies of ſecret Communion with God while in the Wilderneſs, but he was ſo far from being ſatisfied therewithal, that thoſe Taſts he had there ſerved only to increaſe his hungerings, pantings, breathings after <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Sanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, and ſeeing the Glory of God in the beauty of Holineſs, which he had ſeen there. And that is indeed one principal uſe of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotions, to prepare us <hi>for,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our deſires <hi>after</hi> Publique Ordinances
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40711:11"/>
and Fellowſhip with God in them. To take up with them in the Neglect of the other, is croſſe to one of their main ends, and very injurious to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>For the further prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">See <hi>Gurnal's</hi> Epiſt. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat to his Spiritual Armour. pt. 1. pag. 3.</note> of this Doctrine, I ſhal give theſe 2 reaſons</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Becauſe there are a Thouſand times better things to be gotten in the Houſe of God than elſ-where;</hi> and therefore a Day <hi>there,</hi> is better than a Thouſand.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe the attending on God in his Houſe, is the only ſure way to get not only thoſe things ſo much better in value, but even thoſe other things alſo ever and above, for the getting of which the Houſe of God is too frequently neglected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe two Things be demonſtrated, the Doctrine will be abundantly evinced.</p>
            <p>The former Reaſon or Argument may be thus framed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That place where there are things to be ſeen and enjoyed that are a Thouſand times better than thoſe to be had elſe where, is the place in which to be one day is better than a Thouſand,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Houſe of God is the place where there are things to be ſeen and enjoyed that are a Thouſand times beter than thoſe that are to be had elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where</hi>—Therefore one day <hi>there</hi> is better than a Thouſand.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40711:12"/>Of the former.</p>
            <p>Here be the beſt things to be ſeen and gotten; Profit, Pleaſures, Honour are the Idols that the world wonders after, that they ſacrifice their Time, Strength and ſpirits unto: Now that which is true Profit or Gain, real Honour, ſubſtantial Pleaſure is here, and here only to be had.</p>
            <p>Here are true Riches, the Jewel of ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value, which he that gets, gets more than the whole world is worth, and this Pearl is hid in the Field of the Goſpel, incloſed within the Pale of the Courts of Gods Houſe. The product of the Toyl and travel of many a day, is only a little earth. let a man ſearch up and down the world, Compaſs Sea and Land, Ranſack the Bowels of the Earth for the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Treaſures that are there, Tire out himſelf in the Multitude of his way, Waſte away his Time, and wear away his ſtrength, riſe up early and go to bed late and eat the bread of Carefulneſs, and when all is done, what hath he gained? why a very ſmall portion, a poor pittance, that which is ſo far from deſerving the Name of profit that it is a meer vanity and vexation of ſpirit. <hi>Solomon</hi> look'd upon his Houſes, Lands, Gardens, Orchards, Men-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Maid-ſervants, with whatever elſe he had ſpent ſo much time about in the world, and finds that there was <hi>no profit under the Sun;</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40711:12"/>
but in this Market is that rich Commodity to be had which he is a wiſe Merchant who ſells all that he has to purchaſe. It is the Scope of Chriſt (<hi>Prov.</hi> 8.) to prevail with men to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to his voice, come to his Houſe, wait day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at his Poſts, that being inſtructed by him they might be followers of him; N<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ow becauſe he knew men would object the neceſſity of attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their worldly Buſineſs, Farmes &amp; Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize &amp;c He therefore obviates that Objection, that there was more Gain to be gotten at his houſe than in their own Farmes, more profit by hearing his voice than by tilling their Fields, plowing their Land, or by buying &amp; ſelling, and lets them know <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> his Revenues &amp; Merchandize was better than choice Silver or fine Gold, that all the wealth of the world was not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared therewith. <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12. with <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. 13, 14, 15. It is Rational that men ſhould lay out their mony where they may have the moſt ſuitable Commodities &amp; beſt Peniworths, then come to me (ſaith Chriſt) to my Houſe, the Goſpel-market, hear and your ſouls ſhall live, do not lay out your <hi>mony for that which is not bread Iſa.</hi> 55. 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Pleaſures and Delights there are none like thoſe that are to be had in God's Houſe. There is more Sweetneſs in one hour's Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God in his Houſe than in all the pleaſures of ſin for a whole Life-time. See what plentiful Proviſion the Lord makes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40711:13"/>
and invites us to there <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>fat and marrowed things and wine upon the lees.</hi> No Cook dreſſes ſuch meat, no Tavern ſells ſuch drink. The Lord in his Houſe makes ſuch proviſion as abundantly exceeds what is to be found in any other, and thoſe that ſeriouſly attend there, do find abundant ſatisfaction therein. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. 8.—And as for matter of Honour, none like that which God puts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon them who honour him, as all diligent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious waiters upon him in his Houſe emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently do. It is their glory to come near him and behold his Glory, and there (as in the Context <hi>ver.</hi> 11.) he gives glory and that is true Honour indeed. It is the Honour and Glory of <hi>Angels</hi> to be waiting upon God in his upper Houſe of Glory, &amp; of <hi>Men</hi> to wait upon him in his lower houſe of the viſſble Church, where we may both ſee, ſpeak of and partake in his Glory. To be admitted unto near ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to God in his Houſe is a greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; dignity than to be admitted to ſtand <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> &amp; converſe <hi>with</hi> the greateſt Potentates upon earth. If then account themſelvs much honour'd by the Company of great men, much more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is it to be in the <hi>Company</hi> and dwell in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the Great God.</p>
            <p>And that which commends the good things of God's Houſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> above all other, is that they are ſoul-Bleſſings, ſoul-profit, ſoul-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40711:13"/>
&amp;c. Now as much as the Soul is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than all the world, ſo much does ſoul-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit exceed all other profits whatſoever; A little ſoul-good is infinitly better than a great deal of worldly good, and conſequently ſoul-loſs is the worſt loſs. Suppoſe you ſhould gain a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle worldly profit or pleaſure while you might have been at a Sermon, yet you loſe ſoul-profit &amp; pleaſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> while, &amp; then your loſs exceeds your gain. Suppoſe you ſhould be filling your purſe by the one, you are thinning your ſouls by the other; you get bodily refreſhment, comfort &amp;c but you loſe ſoul-benefit, and ſouls-pining will not be recompenſed by your eſtates-thrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. 3. <hi>hear and your ſouls</hi> ſhall <hi>live<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> work, toyl, labour, and your bodies <hi>may</hi> live (tho' poſſibly they mayn't neither) but hear and your ſouls <hi>ſhall</hi> certainly, aſſuredly, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly live. If men would but conſider that they have ſouls, and thereupon ſtudy the worth of them til they find the preference of their ſouls to their bodies, they would then prefer ſoul-enrichments in God's Houſe above all worldly profit or pleaſure in their own, but while men are carnal ſenſual and bruitiſh, minding only their bodies, and thoſe things that do concern their bodies, this Argument will neither be underſtood by them nor be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with them.</p>
            <p>Oh pray the Father of ſpirits, the God that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40711:14"/>
hath made us theſe ſouls, that he would alſo make us to know what our ſouls be, and what is the Concernment of our ſouls, above all other Conſiderations in the world, &amp; then we ſhould realize that the enlightning of the ſoul, converting of the ſoul, reſtoring of the ſoul, Satisfying the hungerings and thriſtings of the ſoul, ſtrengthening us with ſtrength in our ſoul, communion with the dearly beloved of our ſouls, and making our ſouls to rejoyce in Him, the univerſal proſperity of our ſouls, and Salvation of our ſouls at laſt, all which good things are to be attained in God's. Houſe, are the Beſt of all bleſſings and conſequently the attending on God there the moſt profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and delightful of all duties, and by many Thouſand degrees eligible before all other Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment whatſoever.</p>
            <p>More particularly theſe that follow are ſome of thoſe things to be gotten in the Houſe of God that are a Thouſand times better than what are to be had elſe where. <hi>e. g.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Here is the word of God, the powerful enlightening, converting, ſanctifying, ſaving word of God to be heard, and the efficacy of it to be felt and experienced, the Word preached <hi>which is the wiſdome of God and the power of God to ſalvation. Rom,</hi> 1. 16. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 18. 24. The Word by which blind eies are enlightened, deaf ears opened, dead ſouls
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40711:14"/>
quickned, unconverted ones converted, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers brought to the Faith of Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Dayes of being in the Houſe of God are dayes of power, in which God is wont by his Word to ſpeak to the Hearts of poor needy waiters upon him, and makes ſinners a willing people, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 3. Here <hi>David</hi> met with that Word which was more worth to him tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thouſands of ſilver and Gold, and more ſweet than the Honey and the Honey comb. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 10. with 119. 103. He that brings his Heart (not his body only, as many do) to the Houſe of God, and laies it under the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of God's Word there, he by ſo doing laies himſelf in the way of Light and Life, and puts his ſoul under the Influence of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance appointed by God for the conveying of all ſpiritual good to him, it being the Lord's way to do all by his Word. If any of you come to the Houſe of God on a Sabbath day, and there God meet with you and bring your ſouls within the Net of the Goſpel and ſave you, then you will ſay it was the beſt way of ſpending Time that ever you met with. If the Lord ſhall pleaſe to draw you off from your worldly Occaſions and allure you into his Houſe upon a Lecture-day, and there ſpeak to your Hearts, and by his Spirit work upon you for your ſouls everlaſting Good, you will then be as ſo many living Monuments of the Truth of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40711:15"/>
this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> you will have the Witneſs in your ſelves and be able to ſet your ſeals to the experienced verity thereof.</p>
            <p>2. Here is the beſt Company to be had, and ſuch as is a Thouſand Times better than what you will meet with elſe where. And Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is a very attracting thing; for the ſake of <hi>good-fellowſhip</hi> (falſly ſo called) is many an hour and many a good day in God's Houſe loſt, whereas here is that which is truly and deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly called <hi>Good-fellowſhip.</hi> Here <hi>God Father Son</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> are to be ſeen and Converſed with, the Viſion of and Fellowſhip with God are the great things here to be enjoyed. Its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue, God may be ſeen and converſed with elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, but not in that manner and meaſure as here, nor at all ſavingly by thoſe that may but will not wait upon him here. They have ſeen his goings in the Sanctuary <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 24. and ſo may we, the ſight of that Beauty which <hi>David</hi> there deſired <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4. is free for us alſo. This is eminently a Place of drawing near to God, and if you engage your hearts to draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear to him there, he will there meet you and bleſs you <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 24. Now if you can fare ſo well in the Houſe of God as to get a light of him, a good look from him, you will account that Time ſpent unto unparallel'd Advantage. The beholding of God's Beauty (not gazeing on other vain beauties as too many uſually do) ought to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40711:15"/>
be our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrand hither, and will be an heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aviſhing and transforming ſight, and ſo a bleſſed ſight indeed. Here may you ſee the Beauty of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the manifold and matchleſs Beauty of the <hi>LORD, the beauty of his holineſs,</hi> this is to be ſeen in his Houſe which is the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of his Holineſs. The Grace, Mercy, Wiſdom, Power, Love, and Faithfulneſs of God are all of them moſt beautiful things, and theſe are here to be ſeen. To ſee the Lord ſmiling upon a poor Creature and li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting up the Light of his Countenance over him, Oh how beautiful! Why this is eminently to be ſeen in his Houſe, Temple-loving kindneſs worth ſeeing, and worth thinking on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. 9.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially here is the <hi>Glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to be ſeen 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. and be ſure Chriſt has a very beautiful face, He is altogether Lovely and every part of him ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. 10, 16. and in all his Beauty doth he appear in his Houſe, and there is but this one place where he delights in ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious manner and in ſuch a meaſure to ſhew himſelf. Something of God's Glory and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie does appear in the works of Creation and Providence <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 20. but above all doth he unveil his Glory in Jeſus Chriſt and in that great work of Redemption wrought out by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, in the other we may ſee his Footſteps,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40711:16"/>
but in this his Face, and this is a ſight to be ſeen at his Houſe. This glorious, beautiful Draught of the great work of Redemption is hung up in his houſe, his Preſence-Chamber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; expoſed to the view of all comers. Here may you ſee all the Attributes of God concurring &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operating in the Contriveing &amp; bringing about man's Salvation through a Redeemer; The Myſtery of God manifeſted in the Fleſh which the Angels <hi>ſtoop down</hi> to look into (as the <hi>Greek</hi> word imports 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12.) And this manifold Wiſdome of God in Jeſus Chriſt is made manifeſt unto Principalities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by the Church <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 10, 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there they ſee it, thence they learn it.</p>
            <p>There be two Seaſons when eſpecially men deſire to be and appear to be beautiful, and do therefore ſet forth themſelves accordingly <hi>viz.</hi> in their <hi>wooing Time,</hi> and on their Eſpouſal or <hi>Marriage day;</hi> So it is with Jeſus Chriſt: Lords Dayes and Lecture-dayes, when the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is publickly preached, are Chriſts <hi>wooing dayes</hi> and therefore doth he then deck and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray himſelf with all his <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> that he may allure and prevail with men to have him, that being raviſh'd with his Beauty they may conſent to his motion. And Sacrament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes are more eminently the dayes of his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſals</hi> wherein the Covenant that was before ſecretly made between Chriſt and the Soul
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40711:16"/>
when there was a mutual Conſent and promi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> paſſ'd between them, is now more ſolemnly Renewed Sealed and Confirmed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now as a Bride cannot forget her Attire, no more will this great Bride-groom of our Souls neither. This therefore makes <hi>being in the Lords Houſe</hi> ſo much better than <hi>being elſewhere,</hi> becauſe there is Chriſt thus to be ſeen: And a far greater ſight it is than that which (tho' great) was but a ſhaddow of this <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 11. viz. King <hi>Solomon</hi> in the day of his Eſpouſals, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> greater than <hi>Solomon</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing here. On thoſe <hi>Feſtival dayes</hi> doth the Lord Jeſus put on all the Robes of his Grace, Love, Righteonſneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Meekneſs &amp;c that he may appear in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as he is among them. He puts on his red Garments, comes in his Blood and Wound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhews the ſcars of his Combate with the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Salvation, which tho' heart-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſights too, yet in theſe are his Love and Good-will to his people gloriouſly diſcovered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thus their eies are bleſſed with beholding the King in his Beauty <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 17. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Church of Chriſt aſſembled together in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſe of the Ordinances of his Houſe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Temple-Robes, Sanctuary-dreſs, <hi>Holyday</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, regular and exact in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> according to the Order of his Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich is far above the Order of <hi>Solomon's</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:40711:17"/>
that help'd to raviſh the Qeen of <hi>Sheba</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 10. 4, 5.) And further, to ſee Chriſt come in among them according to his promiſe in the Riches of his glorious Grace manifeſting himſelf to them; I ſay to ſee this, is to ſee the moſt Glorious ſight on this ſide of Heaven, yea it is Heaven it ſelf, tho' Heaven upon earth. Hence it is that Sion is ſaid to be beautiful <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. 2. yea and the <hi>Perfection of beauty</hi> Pſal. 50. 2. And we may thank our ſelves if when ever we come to the Houſe of God we do not ſee theſe matchleſs Sights, for Jeſus Chriſt has promiſed his Diſciples <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 20. to be alwaies with them while preaching, and Conſequently with thoſe that are hearing, In the midſt of thoſe that are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Name. In the Ordinances of God's Houſe doth he bring us to Jeſus, and to the <hi>bloud of ſprinkling,</hi> one drop of which if it light on thee there, if being called thither thou have Communion with Chriſt there, no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated good can match it. Here alſo the Spirit of Chriſt is preſent who liſts to be bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his own Ordinances, here you may meet with him ſpeaking <hi>to you</hi> and <hi>in you,</hi> and helping of you, here you may experience the enlightening, teaching, quickening, ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and comforting preſence of the Spirit of Chriſt. And he that ſees and converſes with God in Chriſt in his Houſe, he ſees and enjoyes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40711:17"/>
even all that is worth ſeeing and enjoying, he may ſay to his ſoul, <hi>Return to thy reſt—for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee</hi> Pſal. 116. 7. This is ſuch a filling Comprehenſive enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that it leaves no room for any thing elſe. When Chriſt was diſpoſed to make an eminent diſcovery of his Glory unto meet witneſſes who might afterward give Teſtimony to the world of what they had ſeen, he choſe <hi>Peter</hi> (who had made ſuch a Confeſſion of him and was to ſuffer ſuch great things for him) and <hi>James</hi> (who was the firſt of the Apoſtles that that we read of that laid down his life for Chriſt <hi>Act.</hi> 12. 1.) and <hi>John</hi> the beloved Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple, who was to Live long and do much ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for him, and was favoured with this Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a ſpecial evidence of his Love to him) I ſay he took theſe three and brought them up into the Mount and was transfigured before them <hi>Matt.</hi> 17. 1, 4. upon the ſight of which Excellent glory (as he calls it 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17.) they preſently cry out <hi>it's good being here,</hi> and they might have ſaid (for they meant as much) <hi>it's a Thouſand times better being here than elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, here let us dwell</hi>—(the very Language of <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 27. 4.) They never concerned themſelves about what they ſhould eat or drink or where-with they ſhould be clothed, had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten all their ſecular buſineſs &amp; enjoyments, their Company and Comforts, their Friends
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40711:18"/>
&amp; Families, nay they took no care for ſo much as a place where to lay there Heads, did not once ſpeak of a Tabernacle for themſelves, only for Chriſt and each of the glorious company theſe would build a Tabernacle, and as for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they accounted Chriſt meat and drink and Tabernacle too, ſo were they tranſported and filled with that ineffable <hi>Glory</hi> of Chriſt who is all in all. Thus in the Mountain of the Houſe of God doth the Lord Jeſus reveal and Communicate himſelf as the ſoul-ſatisfying, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling Good. Hence in the cloſe of that <hi>Pſalm</hi> where you have a Record of the Glorious things ſpoken of in God's Houſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87. 8. there is this <hi>Epiphonema</hi> added [<hi>All my ſprings are in thee</hi>] They are either the words of the Spirit of God ſpeaking in his own Name, to ſhew us that in his Houſe are <hi>lay'd up</hi> and in the Word and Ordinances of the ſame are <hi>held forth</hi> and conveyed the waters of Life, all the ſprings of <hi>Grace, Peace, Comfort,</hi> yea of all <hi>Good</hi> whatſoever are there to be had, <hi>All</hi> is there, Or they are the words of a gracious Heart ſpoken by the ſame Spirit implying thus much, that all the ſprings of his Edification and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation as well as of his Regeneration are there; Or that he hath no <hi>Gift</hi> or <hi>Grace, Joy</hi> or <hi>Comfort</hi> or any <hi>Good</hi> worthy of his notice or mention ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what he has there, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to him from thence. Other men have other Comforts, and in other wayes, they have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40711:18"/>
other Ciſterns and Wells (I cannot call them ſprings, at leaſt not living ſprings becauſe they <hi>often</hi> fail &amp; will <hi>utterly</hi> fail in their greateſt need) but <hi>here</hi> the ſincere believing ſoul finds all his Springs, &amp; ſuch as yield him all deſireable Good.</p>
            <p>Of this ſame ſpirit was devout old <hi>Simeon Luk.</hi> 2. 25, 30. who when by the Spirit's conduct he was brought to the Temple and there met with Jeſus Chriſt, he took him in his Arms and and bleſt God and ſaid <hi>now—let me depart in peace &amp;c.</hi> As if he had ſaid with <hi>Jacob</hi> when he heard of Joſeph, <hi>It is enough,</hi> now let me die, I am ſatisfied, farewell vain world with all the ſeeming ſplendor and pretended glory of the ſame, let me now cloſe mine eies, after this ſight I care for nothing elſe, nor is there any other object that I can now be will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to lend ſo much as a look unto, this <hi>Glory of the people Iſrael</hi> (as he calls him <hi>ver.</hi> 32.) hath eclipſed the luſtre and ſtained the beauty of all other glory, I am abundantly repleniſhed with this Sight, ſo that my full ſoul loathes all other ſweets whatſoever, the whole world, yea &amp; life it ſelf is now <hi>nothing</hi> to me, let me now go immediatly to the place of perfect <hi>Viſion &amp; Fruition,</hi> where I ſhall everlaſtingly &amp; uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptedly be ſatisfied with his likeneſs.</p>
            <p>Here alſo may you enjoy the <hi>Communion of Saints Pſa.</hi> 122. 4. and you will meet with no ſuch Company elſe where.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40711:19"/>3. Here is Grace to be gotten, firſt-Grace, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Grace, more Grace, renewed Grace, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring Grace, all manner of Grace, and ſuch meaſure thereof as the Lord hath in his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Wiſdom and Counſel appointed the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Grace</hi> to attain to. The Ordinances of this Houſe of God are ordained and bleſſed by him both for the gathering in or bringing home of the Elect, and alſo for the perfecting of the Saints and edifying the myſtical body of Chriſt <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>Here Faith is infuſed by the word of Faith (<hi>precious Faith</hi> as it is called 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 1.) &amp; by the ſame meanes nouriſhed, ſtrengthened, and increaſed; the like we might ſay of Love, Hope, and the reſt. Now <hi>Grace</hi> is the beſt good, one drop of <hi>Grace</hi> better than an Ocean of Wealth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conſequently a day where <hi>Grace</hi> is going, better than a Thouſand dayes in the Midſt of the Confluence of all other Good things.</p>
            <p>Here are thoſe born that are new-born <hi>Pſal. 87. 5. Jeruſalem</hi> is called the Mother <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 26. and there God doth the part of a Father to beget ſouls to Himſelf; there the Spirit (who breathes where it liſts) liſts to breathe unto Regeneration <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 5, 8. and the place of a man's New-birth is to be preferred before the place of his Birth: men naturally love their Native Soyl, but much more doth the ſpiritual
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40711:19"/>
man affect &amp; delight in the place and meanes of his Converſion. God values the <hi>Gates of Sio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> beyond all Compariſon more than he doth any or all other places, (See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. 2. with 87. 2. &amp; 132. 12, 13.) and not without juſt cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it being dignified with his <hi>Preſence,</hi> beautified with his <hi>Grace;</hi> and filled with his <hi>Glory</hi> above all other places. Now the Saints bearing the Image of their Heavenly Father by whom they are <hi>there</hi> of his own Will by the word of his Truth begotten <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 18. have like Affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion <hi>for</hi> and ſet like price <hi>upon</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p>And being begotten here they are maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here alſo. All the good of the world is no better than Husks to the <hi>Prodigal,</hi> Soul-bread is only to be had in the Father's houſe. As the Breaſt is the life of the new born child, and by a natural Inſtinct he hunts and winds and cries after it; ſo Word and Ordinances in God's Houſe are the nouriſhment, the food, the life of the New Creature, which he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prizes and deſires after 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 2, ſets his Heart unto, and deſervedly becauſe they are his very life <hi>Deut</hi> 23. 47. And indeed could we but realize that the Word of God is (as moſt certainly it is) our Life, we need no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conviction of the worth of it above all other things, &amp; conſequently that being in the Houſe of God where that is deſpenſed is many a Thouſand times better and more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40711:20"/>
than to be any where elſe. The world finds us variety of Buſineſs &amp; Avocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but if the Word preached be ſeen to be of ſuch Concernment, we have a ready Anſwer to to give, here is this and that <hi>may</hi> be done, but we <hi>muſt</hi> live, Life is better than food and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Eſtates. Tell an hungry or a thirſty man that's ready to periſh never ſo many fair ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſet off with the higheſt <hi>Rhetorical</hi> flouriſhes, embelliſhed with oratorical Elegancies, &amp; ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the moſt pleaſing ſtrains of Wit, play him a fitt of Muſick, ſing him the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſong you can think of, hee'll tell you the Belly has no eares, all this is not meat, I muſt eat and drink or dye. The right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the worth of God's Word in his Houſe as it is our appointed &amp; food ſo our life, would make us dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to all the <hi>Syren</hi>-ſongs that the world or the Devil the prince of it could ſing us, whoſe deſign is only to delude and deſtroy us, we ſhould deſpiſe and with indignation turn away from that buſineſs that would draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s away from a Sermon. <hi>I am born</hi> would the New Creature ſay <hi>and I muſt be kept,</hi> I muſt have food or I cannot live, much leſs grow, and I muſt do both, or never be everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saved, and in my Father's Houſe is my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed food prepared for me, and thither muſt I goe that I may feed and live. And hence this is the Return he makes to any pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40711:20"/>
inconſiderable matters that would take him off from this (and all other ſecular Affairs are but little things and inconſiderable matters, compared with this) I am going about a great work, about a matter that concerns my life, and that is and muſt be the Ruleing matter with me, unto which all other things muſt be ſubordinate and give place.</p>
            <p>Had it not been a Birth-right (which was of a ſpiritual nature, and preferible to Life it ſelf) or ſomewhat of like ſort, and had the Caſe been indeed ſo that he muſt have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed that portion of food or immediatly have died without any Remedy, <hi>Eſau</hi> would not have been counted a prophane perſon or a fool for letting it go for a meſs of Pottage, that being univerſally owned <hi>Skin for skin, yea all that man hath will he give for his life, The life being more than meat, and the body—than raiment. Job.</hi> 2. 4. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 23. But juſtly will they be accounted fools that for the ſake of Food and Raiment or that which is of far leſs importance <hi>part with</hi> or <hi>ſlight</hi> that which is their <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Here are all the Benefits of Chriſt held forth, the rich Wares not to be match'd in all the world freely tender'd in this Goſpel-mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, here is <hi>Wine and milk without many and without price Iſa.</hi> 55. 1. Here is Pardon, Peace, Reconciliation, Adoption and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40711:21"/>
               <hi>Chriſt made of God to us wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. Such Commodities as your Ships bring not home, nor are your Shops furniſhed with. The Sea ſaith of theſe things they are not in me, the Earth ſaith they are not in me <hi>Job.</hi> 28. 14, 19. You may with much haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and difficulty go down to the Sea, and dig down into the earth and yet meet with none of theſe things. That Peace is here preached which all your Eſtates cannnot purchaſe, that Peace which the world can neither give nor take away.</p>
            <p>5. I may add this further that is to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Houſe of God <hi>viz.</hi> a ſatisfactory Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of thoſe Enquiries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> an Anſwer to thoſe Doubts and Scruples which pious, ſerious, thinking ſouls are often exerciſed and puzzled with, but by waiting upon God in his Houſe are enlightned and relieved. Hence <hi>David</hi> renders this as one of the reaſons why he made Dwelling in the Houſe of God his <hi>one thing</hi> viz. becauſe he accounted it a good Enquiring-place <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4. beſides that <hi>there</hi> was the Lords Beauty to be ſeen, <hi>there</hi> alſo was a place for enquiring. A child of God is the moſt inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Creature in the world, ſomething he has ſeen, but withal he ſees that there is a great deal more that he hath not ſeen, and hence is for enquiring. Perſons that are ſtudying for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40711:21"/>
Knowledge meet with many queſtions that they cannot anſwer, many Riddles, Knots, Difficulties, that they cannot underſtand, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, ſee through, and therefore chuſe to live near ſuch perſons to whom they may repair for Information. Hence young beginners are trained up in Schools under experienced, knowing Teachers, by whom they may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed as there is occaſion. Now the Houſe of God is the ſchool where the Lord trains up all his Children, there he teacheth them what they know not, and reſolves them in what they are at a ſtand about. More than a few are the Reaſonings that a Believer hath in himſelf, he lives and walks in the midſt of a multitude of Thoughts (eſpecially at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94. 19.) hath many ſcruples in his mind, ſpends many a ſolitary hour in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward doubtings and arguings <hi>pro and con,</hi> and comes often to an Ordinance with his head full of enquiries, and his Heart full of care and fear thereabout; but when he comes to the Houſe of God (and thither he goes to en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>re) he is there ſatisfied, God ſuits a word to his Caſe, orders an Anſwer to that queſtion which he had been long poreing upon to litle pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſpeakes to the ſecrets of his Heart, clears up his doubts and quiets his Spirit; An notable inſtance whereof we find in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. 17. the Pſalmiſt there had been wofully
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40711:22"/>
plunged and dangerouſly ſoiled, inſomuch that he was almoſt gone, was ready to repent him of all his Religion, and that from the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the wicked whom he ſaw ſpared, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched, free from Troubles in their lives and Bonds in their Death, while himſelf (tho' he had cleanſed his Heart and waſhed his hands in Innocency) was plagued all the day long and chaſtened every, morning; Now about this he was at an utter loſs, could not unriddle this Myſtery of Providence, it proved a work too hard for him, to the Sanctuary therefore he goes, &amp; attending upon God there, met with that which anſwered &amp; ſettled him. There he learnt <hi>that no man knows love or hatred by all that is before him.</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 1. There he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that God might out of his abſolute Soveraignty, and for other Reaſons beſt known to himſelf both outwardly proſper the worſt, and ſorely afflict the beſt of men, a Truth which probably he had the notional Knowledge of before but had it not born in upon his Heart with particular application to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Caſe unto his Satisfaction and Comfort till he came into the Sanctuary. Thoſe that <hi>have Chriſt formed in them</hi> are often exerciſed with the like ſtrugglings within them as <hi>Rebeka</hi> had Gen. 25. 21, 22, 23. inſomuch that they are ready to ſay, if it be ſo, why am I thus?
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40711:22"/>
abrupt expreſſions importing Anxiety and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation; But the Word cleares up the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by telling them that there are two men in eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y new Man, and thoſe painful plunges ſhall have a comfortable iſſue in the end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> By enquiring of God <hi>ſhe</hi> got her Anſwer, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may <hi>we,</hi> and the beſt place for Enquireing is the Houſe of God. Satan cannot make more doubts, the Old-man raiſe more ſtorms, the unbelieving Heart cauſe more perplexities than the Lord in his Houſe can anſwer, allay and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tricate out of, and the experience of troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſouls will teſtifie that he is wont ſo to doe, without which there would be no carying on with Comfort.</p>
            <p>In ſumme then, as much as God is more worth than the Creature, Chriſt than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world, Grace than Gold, Pearls than Pebles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Spirituals than Temporals, Wiſdom and its Merchandize than all the Traffick on the Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as much as Heaven is more worth than Vanity, and the Houſe of God which is an Inlet into Heaven exceeds any thing, all-things that this World can produce or afford; ſo much is a day ſpent there in and about theſe more Excellent Things to be rated above a day im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved on any other Account, and ſo the Aſſertion is proved that <hi>One Day in the Houſe of God is better than a Thouſand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40711:23"/>To conlude this Argument, I ſhall a little further enforce and illuſtrate it by making this three-fold Appeal,</p>
            <p>1. To thoſe that have been and are negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in giving their attendance in the Houſe of God, cannot ſpare the Time from their worldly occaſions, ſome keep open their ſhops at Lecture-time, others come into Town &amp; make their market in the morning and away again before the Sermon, others walk the ſtreets, fit in Taverns or ſtay in their own Houſes while the Sermon is Preaching, and I would ask you what do you gain? what profit do you make of this two Hours Time in a week thus ſaved from the Publick Worſhip of God, ask your ſelves ſeriouſly and anſwer truly what is your gain? how much does it amount to in a day's nay in a year's Time? why one takes a few pence in his ſhop, another earns a few by a ſmall Jobb of work done the while, another redeems an hour or two from a ſermon and gets ſo much the ſooner about his occaſions at home, another gets a little eaſe, a little ſleep, a little drink, and idle, vain Chatt together with it, and I beſeech you what does it come to? what is your eſtate advanced or your ſelves any way bettered at the years end? Nay are you not loſers every manner of way? Did they who neglected God's Houſe whom the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> reproves <hi>Chapt.</hi> 1. gain any
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40711:23"/>
Thing by their labour in or about their own houſes, or in their Fields while plowing ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or gathering in? No they were curſed in their Employment, blaſted in their Labours, the Lord did blow upon their Harveſt and the wages they earned was put in a bag with Holes, all that they did turned to little or no Account, nothing ſucceeded with them. God is the ſame and the Concerns of his Houſe of as great value as ever, and his Anger as hot <hi>now</hi> for ſlighting and neglecting his Ordinances as <hi>then;</hi> ſo that could you take an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count you'd ſee cauſe to own your ſelves lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers even in your outward eſtate, and if Blaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Mildews, Loſſes by Sea and Land, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointments, Impoveriſhments many waies were lookt at as a juſt puniſhment from God for the great Coldneſs dead-heartedneſs and indiſpoſedneſs, to the Worſhip of God in his Houſe in ſpecial, among other ſins that are to be found among us, there would be good Scripture warrant for our ſo reckoning. Men complain Trading is dead, they do not thrive, they go behind hand, cannot make both ends meet, they riſe early, go to bed late, eat the bread of Carefulneſs and all will not doe, No wonder while God's Houſe is under-valued and neglected.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe thou may'ſt gain a ſmall matter while thou ought'ſt to have been at a Sermon,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40711:24"/>
and for the gains thereof didſt omit an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſeeing and Converſing with Chriſt in an Ordinance, he judges your ſelves in the Caſe whether you are Gainers or loſers. A few pence gain'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a goodly price that I was valued at will Jeſus Chriſt ſay: And take this for an everlaſting Truth, the ſame price we put upon the Word of Chriſt, we put upon Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: We condemn Judas for betraying his Maſter for Thirty peices of Silver, <hi>But who art thou O man that judgeſt another and doeſt the ſame thing?</hi> He that cannot find in his heart to come to a Sermon for fear to miſs the taking or earning a little mony would ſell Jeſus Chriſt himſelf at a cheaper Rate than ever Judas did, if he had the like Temptation before him, Nay he does part with him, let him goe (yea &amp; that for ought he knows irrecoverably &amp; forever) for the love, of that which he propoſes to himſelf to gain in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean time. If you will not now believe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a little Time will put it beyond diſpute. When an evil day comes, and you want thoſe words to live upon that you might have then heard; and that Inſtruction and Edification that you might have gained, Conſcience will then tell you that you ſinned by ſuch Neglect and got no profit. <hi>Martha</hi> got a ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof by being careful and cumbered with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, while ſhe ſhould have ſate at Chriſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et and been hearing a Sermon; and ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40711:24"/>
ſhall you have from your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences one day, and ſhould take them now. No man ſhall ever gain in the winding up by that Time that he pinches out of the Service of God whether Publique, Private, or Secret.</p>
            <p>2. My ſecond Appeal is to thoſe that have ſubordinated all other things to the Service of God, and can make their ſecular Occaſions give way thereunto, and conſequently have been and are Careful, Faithful attenders on His Word and Ordinances; and I would ask you, Did you ever loſe, did you not ever gain by being ſo imployed? Have you not cauſe to account thoſe your beſt Houres? Had you ever any juſt Cauſe to repent of your Time ſo ſpent? Would you part with what you have met with in the Houſe of God for a Thouſand Worlds? Are not all other pleaſures and profits moſt inconſiderable and contemptible things compared with what God's Houſe has afforded you? Say, ſpeak out, that others may be informed and confirmed by your expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience. Have you not found that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, that Quickning, that Edifying power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Grace accompanying Divine Inſtitutions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was no where elſe to be found, and that you could never pretend to any thing like thereto from all your Labours about the World?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:40711:25"/>Is not this Doctrine true, have you not found and felt it true? cannot you <hi>give your Evidence in the Caſe?</hi> Then ſpeak for God and for his Houſe, ſtand up for the Honour of the ſame. Tell one another as you have oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of the Good things there, diſcourſe together of the rich Entertainment you have met with, and as you meet with others to whom ſuch diſcourſes may be of uſe, let them know how you have fared there. The world does not believe that the <hi>fooliſhneſs of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> has ſuch vertue in it as the report of the Word attributes to it, any more than <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neel</hi> could believe that <hi>any Good could come out of Nazareth;</hi> do you therefore teſtifie to what you have ſeen, and adviſe them alſo to come and ſee.</p>
            <p>3. My third Appeal is to thoſe that after they have ſometimes enjoyed, have again loſt the Liberties of God's Houſe (and thoſe that have experienc'd both the ſweetneſs of the enjoyment and the bitterneſs of the bereave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are beſt able to judge in this Caſe) Now they will all tell you with one month that there is no place to ſpend Time in like the Houſe of God. And ſuch is the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>Text;</hi> He had lived at the Well-head, been often drinking of the waters of the Sanctuary, and abundantly ſatisfied with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40711:25"/>
the Good things thereof, he had lived near the green Meadowes and ſtill waters, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently taken his ſweet repaſt there, he had ſeen the Lord's Glory and Beauty in the Sanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uary and had been enlightned, quickned and comforted there, for which Favours you have him in ſundry Pſalms tuneing his Harp and Pſaltery and fixing his heart to the Praiſes of God, and bleſſing himſelf and the people in thoſe high enjoyments, in reſpect of which God had ſo dealt with Iſrael as with no other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But now you find him in quite another Frame, longing, fainting, Crying out like a perſon in great diſtreſs, fareing like a poor forlorn, miſerable wretch, in a ſtate moſt ſadly afflictive and deplorable, intimating that he could have been glad to change Conditons with the Swallow and Sparrow, when he ſeems to envy that priviledge which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed and he was bereaved of; what was the matter? what ail'd him? why alas this was his Caſe (a. woful Caſe indeed!) that ſweet, precious, beloved place the <hi>Houſe of God</hi> he could not come at, thoſe Glorious and gainful daies which he had with ſo much pleaſure and advantage ſpent were now paſt and gonae with him, and when or how to be recovered he knew not, and he ſo demeans himſelf as one that both underſtood what he ſaid, and ſaid as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40711:26"/>
he meant when he ſet ſo high a value upon one of thoſe daies.</p>
            <p>Of like nature and ſcope is <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. and had you ſeen him at that Time when he Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it, you would have found him in a moſt ſolemn frame, his eyes weeping and himſelf making meat of his tears when he had wept them, his Heart beating and panting, his ſoul fainting and poured out within him, and had you conſulted with him he would have told you this lamentable ſtory, I once dwelt in Sion, and had mine Habitation in Jeruſalem, that pleaſant place where the Lines were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen me, &amp; where I had a goodly Heritage &amp; had free acceſs to the Houſe of God, &amp; thither was wont to go <hi>with the Company that kept Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> but now I am an Out-caſt from the Temple in the land of <hi>Jordan</hi> and the <hi>Hermonites,</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to Meeting, I cannot hear a Sermon as I was wont, by the loſs of which Mercy I have learnt (ſomewhat more than ever) the worth of it, a loſs that can by no other attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be compenſated.—This was the cauſe of his mourning, and the inward diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and caſting down of his ſoul, and this alſo cauſed him to make that Prayer in the following Pſalm <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4. that God would conduct him back to his Holy Hill and to his Tabernacles, that he might again goe to the Altar of God his exceeding Joy, and promiſes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40711:26"/>
his praiſes for the hearing of his prayer, nor would any thing raiſe up his down-caſt ſoul but the Hopes that thoſe prayers ſhould be heard. And it is to be noted in both th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Pſalms (the like alſo may be obſerved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſe where) when bemoaning his Exilement he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver once mentions his own Houſe or his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or family Concerns all which were (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond diſpute) according to the value of each very dear to him, but this is the matter with him, <hi>the Houſe of God!</hi> And ſo when he was driven out of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſaies nothing of his Kingdom, or Palace, or any Relations he left behind, only the Ark and its Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Houſe of God where the Lord dwelt and afforded his Preſence, <hi>This, this</hi> I ſay he thought and diſcourſed of, and thereby ſhewed what lay at his Heart, and how much he prized them above other Things which he accounted not worthy to be mentioned the ſame day with theſe. Thus alſo when ſick <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had the Sentence of Death (that was upon him) reverſed, and an Addition of fifteen Years promiſed, he asked a ſign where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might be aſſured about his going up again to the Houſe of God, as if he had valued his Time of going thither more than all his Time beſides, or as if his repri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>val from the Grave were therefore principally
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40711:27"/>
grateful to him becauſe he might have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of rendering the Lord a further viſit there <hi>Iſa:</hi> 38. 22. the fear of ſeeing the Lord no more (probably he means in his Houſe the chief place for ſeeing God) having been moſt grievous to him in his ſickneſs <hi>ver.</hi> 11. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he engaged that he would not only goe up thither but dwell there to praiſe him all the daies of his life.</p>
            <p>And at this day how many juſt and Righteous ones are there in the world that are begging on their knees with Tears in their eies that they might enjoy one of theſe dayes of the Son of Man that we have plenty of, they would wonder to ſee the ſtreets and ſhops ſo full of people while a Sermon is a preaching which they would gladly leave their very meat to hear. what a Pathetical lecture would they read you of the worth of Sermons and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances! How feelingly would they diſcourſe of theſe things and tell you that whatever outward good things are left them they do all avail them little or nothing while baniſhed from the Houſe of God, and how affectionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would they exhort and beſeech us to <hi>know i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this our day the things of our peace,</hi> to improve every inch of Hearing-Timé, and that with utmoſt Seriouſneſs and Intenſneſs, to believe them while they do give evidence to the Truth of this Doctrine, and in ſo doing ſpeak what
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40711:27"/>
they have ſeen and felt, leſt we alſo pay dear for our learning (as they have done) that <hi>one day in the Courts of the Lord is worth a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much may ſerve for the firſt Reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Argument.</p>
            <p>The ſecond followes.</p>
            <p>Reaf. 2. <hi>One day in God's Houſe is better than a Thouſand,</hi> Becauſe ſerious waiting there is not only the way to have theſe unparaleld Bleſſings already mentioned, but alſo the fureſt and ſafeſt way to obtain all other Good things which we need, and for the getting of which the Houſe of God is too often neglected, yea and to have them ſanctified and ſecured too. This being cleared will evince the Truth of the Doctrine againſt all Gain-ſayers.</p>
            <p>This is the common Objection, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n cannot come to Meeting on a Lecture-Day becauſe their buſineſs will not give leave, this and that work calls for their preſence, or elſe they ſhall be great ſufferers. The Husband-man (eſpecially in ſeed-Time and Harveſt) has no leiſure, he muſt get his ſeed into the Ground and his Harveſt into the Barn. The day-La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer gets his Living by the ſweat of his Browes, and <hi>has but from hand to mouth,</hi> and therefore he can ſpare no time for the Worſhip
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40711:28"/>
of God. The Handicraft's man has work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken, and muſt <hi>keep touch,</hi> leſt he loſe his Cuſtome, The Shop-keeper will tell you Rent is high, Trading dead, he has a Family to maintain and therefore muſt loſe no opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of taking Mony, and Lecture-dayes are his Market-dayes and he cannot leave his ſhop, tho' if none did appear to buy (as mee thinks none ſhould that did conſider that the doors of Chriſt's Houſe are then open, where better Commodities are to be bought viz. <hi>Wine and milk,</hi> ſoul-maintenance, and that <hi>without mony and without Price</hi>) there would be no occaſion for him to ſit there to ſell. Thus when men want an Heart they never want an excuſe, thoſe that have no mind to a Duty will find pretences enough to colour over their neglect of it: But it were an eaſie matter to Retort the Arguments upon themſelves &amp; they would argue more ſtrongly the other way. Is not your buſineſs for Heaven of as great Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Half? are you ſo forward, ſo much before hand therein as that without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Dammage you can ſpare ever and anon a Sermon and not miſs it? Is not a Seed-time and an Harveſt-time for your <hi>meat that endures to eternal Life</hi> as buſie a time with you as that wherein you are labouring for the <hi>meat that periſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th?</hi> Is not the Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are in <hi>riſing betimes and ſending</hi> to you, and that both
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40711:28"/>
               <hi>in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon</hi> an Intimation that the Lord ſees you need ſuch Diſpenſations, for he does no needleſs thing. Have you not as much need to take every ſeaſon and lay up for endleſs Eternity as to provide againſt a long Winter? Eſpecially when you conſider that you are going <hi>towards,</hi> and know not how ſoon you may come <hi>to</hi> the place where <hi>there is no Work, Device nor Invention Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 10. Have you ſuch a meaſure of knowledge as that it needs no Augmentation? ſuch a ſtock of Grace lying by you that you need no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of it? Or are your Graces ſo active as that you have no occaſion for Word and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to excite them and keep them in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe? Is not Trading for Heaven very dead alſo, ſo that there is much cauſe for the Lord to complain as of old <hi>I have laboured in vain Iſa.</hi> 49. 4.? and will not the loſs of Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offers (as puniſhments for the ſlights you put upon them) be a greater Detriment than the loſs of a good Cuſtomer for want of complying with him? Nay ſhould not your Care and Thoughtfulneſs, Labour and Diligence about the things of <hi>this Life</hi> teach you that then much more ought your Activity to ſhew it ſelf about Things of a <hi>better?</hi> Might not ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations as theſe afford you a ſilencing An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſuch Excuſes?</p>
            <p>But let me further add</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40711:29"/>That even this is the way to promote your worldly Advantage too, the words immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately following the Text are a proof of it. After the Pſalmiſt had given his judgment upon a day in God's Houſe above a Thouſand, and made his Choice of being a door-keeper there rather than a dweller elſe where, he gives the reaſon of his ſo chooſing, and its taken from the Good things there to be had, <hi>viz.</hi> Grace and Glory, but leſt any ſhould ſay what ſhall we do for other things, he adds, <hi>No good thing will he with-hold &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt ſpeakes the ſame thing <hi>Mat. 6. 33. Seek firſt the Kingdom of God &amp; his righteouſneſs, &amp; all other things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> Whatever elſe is wanting ſhall be given into the Bargain, caſt in over and above. That Kingdom which you principally, firſtly ſeek ſhall be given you, and all other things ſhall be ſupplied alſo. Honouring the Lord with our ſubſtance (and by the like reaſon with our Time ſpent in his Service as we have an Opportunity) is the way to have <hi>the Barn filled with plenty &amp;c. Prov.</hi> 3. 8, 10. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote this ſearch after Wiſdom (<hi>and waiting at Wiſdom's poſts is the way to find Wiſdom Pro.</hi> 8. 34.) he tells us that <hi>Riches and Honours are in her left hand Chapt.</hi> 3. 16. It is not Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Contriving, but God's bleſſing that makes Rich. Now the dayly Waiter and Watcher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Wiſdom's Gates to hear Chriſt is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40711:29"/>
pronounced <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> he is the man that is under God's bleſſing and therefore ſhall have ſo much of other things alſo as is convenient for him. In Commendation of Godlineſs, &amp; to promote the practice of it, it is ſaid to be <hi>great Gain</hi> and the <hi>promiſe of the life that now is</hi> as well as <hi>that which is to come</hi> made to it 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. And he that hath any Good Thing in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is as ſure of it as if it were in his hand, yea coming in a Promiſe it's far more ſweet and ſafe than if it came in the way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Providence. That known Text <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 8, 12. does abundantly anſwer the Objection and prove the Poſition before us, they are faulted <hi>ver.</hi> 8. for Robbery in the matters of God's Houſe, they brought not in their Tythes and Offerings, the reaſon of their with-hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them is hinted at <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the Worſhip of God to be too charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for them, they could not afford to goe to the coſt of it. Nay (ſaith the Lord) if that be the Reaſon, do you fill my Houſe and ſee if I will not fill yours and abundantly make up to you what Expence ſoever you ſhall be at by ſerving me. While you Robb'd me I curſt you, and if you will obey me in the matters of my Houſe I will bleſs you.</p>
            <p>From this Text theſe things are Evident</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40711:30"/>
               <item>1. That men are prone to deal very unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily with God in the Concerns of his Houſe and are apt to be too ſtrait-handed there.</item>
               <item>2. One Reaſon of their ſo carrying it is for fear they ſhould loſe in their outward Eſtate thereby, they cannot tend it, they cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford it is the pretenſe, tho' its true <hi>they have no heart to it</hi> lies at the bottom.</item>
               <item>3. That ſo to do is in God's account Rob bery, &amp; is puniſhed with a Curſe, the Vine caſts her fruit, the Devourer eats up their Labours and inſtead of ſaving they are great loſers thereby.</item>
               <item>4. That the only way to be bleſt in their Labours and to thrive in the world, is to fill God's Houſe, to give their attendance there with their Tythes and Offerings let them not be wanting in their duty to him, and he would abundantly make up to them what they laid out for him: And tho' the Lord is worthy to be believed upon his word, yet he condeſcends ſo far as to put things upon the Tryal <hi>Prove me ſaith the Lord,</hi> if you will not believe me try me, and you ſhall find it true, while my Houſe was empty ſo were yours alſo, and what you pinch't from me you loſt, and a great deal more with it, but upon your amending ſee if I will not proportionably and obſervably bleſs you.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40711:30"/>You never knew any man impoveriſhed by ſpending two houres in a week at a Lecture, nor enriched by the Contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I have heard of a poor man being asked by a pious Miniſter why he came not to Lect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure, anſwered not want of will but meer Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty hindred him, for <hi>that</hi> day in which he did not work his children muſt not eat, being adviſed by the Miniſter to come to Lecture, and promiſed to be paid for his dayes work he readily came to Meeting, and as conſtantly for his Pay at Night, but after a little Time being ask'd the Reaſon why tho' at Lecture he came not for his mony as formerly, he ſaid that he found God had ſo bleſt him that he could main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Family by his labour and ſpare a Lecture time too.—</q> And if others will try in like manner they ſhall have the like bleſſing.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid <hi>Mony anſwers all things</hi> Eccl. 10. 19. yea but the Bleſſing of God in the way of ſerious attending on him in his Houſe will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer mony alſo, will ſupply that too. God hath many ſecret waies to bleſs his ſervants, and doth abundantly ſend in what we lay out for him. Our Fathers in this Wilderneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd this, they came for the ſake of God's Houſe, and he ſoon filled theirs, turned the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40711:31"/>
Wilderneſs into a fruitful Land, gave them what they denyed and left behind them for his and the Goſpel's ſake. And while the <hi>firſt love</hi> and zeal for Chriſt and the things of his Houſe were kept up they had much outward proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; our coldneſs there has brought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thinneſs and leanneſs both outward and ſpiritual upon us.</p>
            <p>This alſo is the ſure way to have all our other good things ſanctified to us: By the Word and prayer are all our outward bleſſings ſanctified 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 5. and without this they are a ſnare and Trap. If men would obſerve, there is none but loſes as much and more than he gains by robbing God of his Time, or at leaſt he loſes the bleſſing, and what is the outward enjoyment without a Bleſſing? why, it is for his hurt rather than for his good, and its better to want ſuch things in mercy than to have them in wrath.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſerve for the Confirmation of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>We come now to the Application or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement,</p>
            <list>
               <head>And this word is profitable for</head>
               <item>Information or Inſtruction</item>
               <item>Reproof or Correction</item>
               <item>Exhortation &amp; Direction.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. by way of Information and Inſtruction</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40711:31"/>1. See here the Wiſdome of God in provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo well for the promoting of his own pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Worſhip while he orders ſo much profit to attend the waiters upon him therein, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by obviating the objections that may be made againſt it, &amp; that great one eſpecially <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>what profit is it that we have ſerved God and kept his Ordinance?</hi> What profit? more than <hi>Cent. per Cent.</hi> profit, even a Thouſand to one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and that is great gain indeed. The Lord out-bids all that ever the world, or the Devil the god of the world can do for his followers<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>Reaſon ſhould teach us to go into <hi>his</hi> vineyard where we may have the moſt pleaſant work and beſt wages. Did men underſtand and believe, there would be no great difficulty in this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> to weaken <hi>David</hi>'s Intereſt in the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and draw them off from him, intimates that they could not expect much profit or high preferment from the ſon of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> (1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 7.) inſinuating that where there is an expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the greateſt Reward, there men would be moſt like to be found. Then God may well expect that we ſhould prefer his Houſe before our own houſes, Fields, Ships or Shops, becauſe all of them cannot yield the like profit by more than a Thouſand to one Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. He muſt needs account God not worthy to be believed, or Fellowſhip with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40711:32"/>
him in his Houſe not worthy to be enjoyed, that is not perſwaded (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pitty any ſhould need to be compell'd) there to dwell, and to Improve all opportunities of Seeing and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring there. Wiſdom invites m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to <hi>her</hi> Houſe <hi>Prov.</hi> 9. and the fooliſh one calls upon Simple ones that are going right on, to turn in thither, the former invites to beaſts ſlain, Wines mingled and Table furniſhed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes life upon obedience (<hi>hear and your ſouls ſhall live Iſa.</hi> 55. 3.) The latter ſpeaks on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of water and bread, and that ſtollen and in ſecret too, concealing in the mean time Death and depths of Hell the puniſhment of deluded fools. Mee thinks none need be at a loſs at which houſe to turn in. Chriſt would be no way offended for turning our backs upon his Ordinances if we knew any place where to mend our ſelves, but to leave him for lying vanities makes him angry.</p>
            <p>There is nothing but Atheiſm and Unbelief that keeps any poor creature from making this his <hi>One thing</hi> to dwell in the Houſe of God.</p>
            <p>2. Hence we are further Informed how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful the Lord is of us alſo &amp; of our Good as well as of the promoting his own ſervice, in that he does not oblige us to do any ſervice for him, nor to ſpend one day or hour but ſo as ſhall be to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40711:32"/>
our own higheſt advantage. No Worſhip of God ſhall interfere with our profit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He will diſpence with his Worſhip when works of neceſſity and mercy for our ſelves or others beſpeak our Attendance, and he never enjoyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it but it is beſt for us and moſt for our good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> This is great kindneſs indeed to poor Creatures that He will not be ſerved but when we ſhall be profited, and has ſo diſpoſed that it is alwaies for our profit to ſerve Him. If we were rightly affected towards God we ſhould need no more or other Argument than this to bring us to the Houſe of God and oblige us to the moſt ſerious attendance <hi>viz.</hi> that we are about God's work, doing <hi>Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſervice, that he will be glorified thereby, would be enough to us; but the Lord will have us to know that we are then about our own work alſo, and that which moſt nearly concerns us and will unſpeakably advantage us. Altho' we muſt deny our ſelves and take much pains to ſerve God, if we do it acceptably, yet all this while we are working for our ſelves, and the Harveſt will be our own, and that a Thouſand times more than we could have gotten elſe where. You will ſay when the Beggars that lay by the High-waies and Hedges were invited to the Marriage-feaſt they were not bidden to their loſſe, no, nor they that had Farms and Merchandize neither, they never had ſuch Incomes nor made ſuch
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40711:33"/>
Bargains as they might have had and made there. Let none think it hard that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires one day in ſeven for the more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſervice of Himſelf, nay if he ſhould require ſix of the ſeven and leave us but one, while he gives us the profit of more than a Thouſand dayes in one, there is no colour for any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. The Lord commanded them in the Wilderneſs to reſt on the Sabbath day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and gives this as a reaſon why they ſhould ſo doe, becauſe he had on the ſixth day given them the Bread of two dayes <hi>Exod.</hi> 16. 29.. So when he commands us to wait on him in his Houſe on a Lecture-day (and by the way do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that attending on Lectures is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a free-will offering, tho' if it were ſo, God's people ſhould be <hi>a willing people,</hi> and willing in their free-will Offerings, but that General Rule of taking all Opportunities of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and conſequently of getting Good is not without its Conſideration here, and if the Miniſter be charged to <hi>preach—in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. 2. by like reaſon the people are obliged to hear) doe not think we are hardly dealt with, ſtraitned in our time, abridged of our liberty <hi>to labour and do all that we have to doe on the ſix dayes</hi> ſeeing our own profit is propounded and ſuch profit as has been mentioned, to induce us thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:40711:33"/>If a company of poor indigent people ſhould be ordered by ſome great Perſon to wait at his Gate two hours on ſuch a day in the week, there to receive a liberal Dole from his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Hand, they would account themſelves bountifully dealt with while they had ſo much more given them than they could have gotten by <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>their own induſtry in the mean Time; And that is the Caſe before us.</p>
            <p>3. This alſo Informs us how much we ſtand Debtors in God's Account for every day's Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in his Houſe, he ſets down a Thouſand for One and after that Rate will reckon with us, and therefore we ſhould reckon ſo alſo, and hold our ſelves engaged to make an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable improvement of them that we may render proportionably. This is the choice, the Cream, the Quinteſſence of all our Time, for this eſpecially are wee bound to lift up our eyes and ſouls and bleſs the name of the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful God, and that a Thouſand times more than for any other Time. Thanks are to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> proportion to the quantity of the Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs received: As they that have much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given will love much, ſo they that have much given ſhould thank much, praiſe much, which they will do if they love much. We ſhould bleſs God heartily every morning we riſe, for bringing us to the Light of another day, but
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40711:34"/>
we ſhould bleſs him a Thouſand times more for a day in his Courts, becauſe it is a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times better. It was an exceeding great and precious Promiſe that the Lord gave to his People <hi>Iſa</hi> 30. 20. a rich &amp; high Cordial fitted on purpoſe for an evil day that tho their meat ſhould be bread of Adverſity and drink water of Affliction yet <hi>their eyes ſhall ſet their Teachers,</hi> they ſhall have Preaching and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances among them. Alas, how many have bread of Adverſity and their Teachers remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too! How ſhould the ſcarcity of that <hi>Beſt of all Commodities</hi> ſerve to enhaunce the price of it! All our Time is precious, but this part of our Time much more precious than the reſt. Many account Sabbath-dayes loſt-dayes, and Lecture-dayes broken dayes, no, they are good dayes and full dayes, dayes full of Bleſſing, one of them has the Good of a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand daies in it. Some had rather ſickneſs or Foul-weather ſhould fall out an a Sabbath-day or on a Lecture-day than any other, &amp; ſecretly think it is ſo much Time ſaved, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſidering how much the Wiſdom and kindneſs of God is thereby Reflected upon, and themſelves preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced.</p>
            <p>4. Hence we may learn what is the beſt Courſe to redeem Time, which is a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon all Chriſtians <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:40711:34"/>
The ſpending as much of it as you may i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Houſe of God is the beſt way of Redeeming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> If men were good Husbands of their Time, it were an eaſie matter to ſave ever and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non a Day for the Service of God and yet not ſtrike one ſtroak the leſs about their other ordinary Occaſions; and one day thus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, provided it be rightly improved ſo as to become a good day to them, is more than a Thouſand dayes.</p>
            <p>5. From hence alſo it followes, that it is a greater Bleſſing to a People to have the Liberties of God's Houſe than to have a Confluence of all this World's Good flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon them. They are better that enjoy the Houſe of God among them, tho' they are ſtraitened in other outward Things, than they which have the greateſt outward Enlargements without it.</p>
            <p>God ſo orders it, that the Richeſt places in the World (as to Things of the World) are very poor upon this account, while <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> People tho' dwelling in a Barren Land have the Riches of Earth and Heaven both, in having the Houſe of God among them. Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings of Ephraim are better than the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Abiezer. Suppoſe a Place in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Temperate Zone, that is an healthy Climate,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40711:35"/>
has a ſweet Air, pleaſant Situation, fertile Soyl, Havens for Ships, a place of great Trade and much Reſort, ſo that what they have not of their own they may bring home (tho' from far) out of other places; Imagine an <hi>Eden</hi> of all manner of pleaſures and Delights, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all theſe Conſiderations and Circumſtances it is a miſerable place if the Houſe of God be wanting. That poor ſolitary Pilgrim <hi>Jacob,</hi> lying in the open Air, having the cold Earth for his Bed, and a ſtone for his Pillow yet the place being turned into a <hi>Bethel,</hi> an Houſe of God he fared better than if he had been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ommodated with all the Entertainment that a Princes Palace could have afforded him. <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſs tho' dwelling in Tents, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with bread and Water without the Fleſh-pots of <hi>Egypt</hi> and other good things they ſo much longed for, yet being the Church in the Wilderneſs, and having God's Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle in the midſt of them, were in a far hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier Condition than the Canaanites who dwelt in a land flowing with Milk and Honey but no Houſe of God near them.</p>
            <p>Our Fathers coming into this Wilderneſs, and bringing Chriſt and the Ordinances of his Houſe along with them, never repented them of the Exchange they had made, nor were ſo mindful of the pleaſant Land from whence they came as to return thither again, tho' they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40711:35"/>
had opportunities of ſo doing See <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 15. Nay the Lord prevented them by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wilderneſs into a fruitful Land, and the Houſe of God ſet up and attended will make any place ſo. After the large De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of that great City given by the Prophet Ezekiel, we find its real Glory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the name by which it was called viz. <hi>Jehovah ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mma.</hi> The Temple of the Lord and his preſence in the Temple renders a place glorious. Never complain of Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and Difficulties, the Conſideration of the Tranſcendent Goodneſs of God to be enjoyed in his Houſe ſhould ſwallow up all Difficulties whatſoever. Dwelling in Tents of wickedneſs, nay in the Palaces of the World is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed in Compariſon of dwelling here. He that for Elbow-room in the World removes from under Word &amp; Ordinances makes a very imprudent Choice. Its Religion, not any nor all other things that <hi>makes</hi> a place. It was the Preſence, Houſe and Worſhip of God in the Land of Canaan principally that made it the <hi>Glory of all Lands, the Land of Glory or the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Land</hi> (as it is called Ezek. 20. 6. Dan. 11. 16, 41.) Its therefore glorious becauſe it is <hi>Immanuel's land Iſa.</hi> 8. 8. This Mount Sion ſo beautiful a place, becauſe <hi>out of Sion the perfection of beauty God hath ſhined Pſal.</hi> 50. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:40711:36"/>Prize Goſpel-Ordinances and Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in them as the chiefeſt Glory of our Land, and evermore pray that ſuch Glory may alwayes <hi>dwell</hi> in our Land.</p>
            <p>6. Then we ſhould above all other Things fear loſing a day in God's Houſe, yea fear lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Houſe of God</hi> and being <hi>outed</hi> of our Poſſeſſion thereof. According to the value of a thing is our Love to it, Deſire to keep it, Fear to loſe it. Now if being in God's Houſe is a Thouſand times better than other-where; then we ſhould be a Thouſand times more afraid about that than any thing elſe. It is now a Time of Fear with us, ſome fear they ſhall loſe this thing, ſome that, and ſome another, but above all fear and tremble for the <hi>Ark,</hi> fear for the <hi>Houſe &amp; Ordinances of GOD, there</hi> is moſt Cauſe of Fear, we have a Thouſand times more cauſe to fear for God's Houſe than for our own houſes, lands &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if we are providentially kept from the Houſe of God by Sickneſs or otherwiſe, it ſhould afflict us more than being kept from our own buſineſs. To have loſt a day through any inadvertency or neglect of his own, or through any Adverſe Providence that has diſappointed him in his Expectation or blaſted his Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, is afflictive to an induſtrious man: but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:40711:36"/>
to have loſt a day from or in the Houſe of God, ſhould be by many degrees more grievous to a ſerious ſoul; nor ſhould our being driven out of our own houſes be ſo yrkſome to us as the Lord's plucking up ſtakes, or breaking up houſe among us. We live in Times of Plucking up and pulling down, to be now <hi>ſeeking great Things for our ſelves in the world</hi> would be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and blame worthy <hi>Ier.</hi> 45. but to be ſeeking the greater things of God's Houſe, and to be moſt Thoughtful about the Continuance thereof, and our dwelling therein all the dayes of our life, is very becoming in us, and will be no leſs acceptable unto God. The only way to ſecure what is our own is to be moſt ſolicit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous about the concerns of God's Houſe; let our Hearts be mainly there, and then we may roul the Burden of all other Cares upon him.</p>
            <p>7. This Doctrine doth intimate to us with what ſpirit and Frame we ſhould go, when ever we go to the Houſe of God <hi>viz.</hi> with an high eſteem of it, &amp; Expectation of great things in &amp; from it. Value an hour there worth a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and expect to receive accordingly. They had no more becauſe they <hi>ask<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> no more <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 2, 3. and we have no more becauſe we <hi>expect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> no more. There is ordinarily ſome proportion between our Receivings and our Expectations; and the Reaſon is becauſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40711:37"/>
ariſing from the ſence of our need and the reallizing that <hi>there</hi> is a ſupply to be had, and being accompanied with anſwerable preparation and Attention, bring us under a promiſe. The Text tells us there is a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more to be had in the Houſe of God than elſe-where, then we ſhould expect as much as the Word ſaith, and the Lord is not wont to fail his people of their Expectations <hi>Pſal. 9. 18. The Expectation of the poor ſhall not periſh.</hi> But we may add ſomething further to this in the ſequel.</p>
            <p>8. Is one Day in God's Houſe better than a Thouſand, then the Lord expects that they who dwell in his Houſe ſhould <hi>be</hi> better and <hi>doe</hi> better than other men. <hi>Where much is given much is required.</hi> They who live in His Houſe fare better than any others, are <hi>known above all the families of the earth Amos 3. 2. He hath not dealt ſo with any other Nation Pſal.</hi> 147. 20. Such have better Liberties, better meanes, better opportunities, (a Thouſand times better) than thoſe who are not thus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; and therefore their knowledge, their principles, their Hearts and Converſations ſhould be better. If any Heathen have more moral Honeſty, Sobriety, Love &amp;c. than we, beware ſuch do not riſe up in Judgment againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, condemn and triumph over us in the Day of Account. The Lord does (and juſtly may)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40711:37"/>
look for better Grapes from his Vineyard upon which he had beſtowed ſuch coſtly and careful Husbandry, and in the midſt of which Himſelf dwelt, than he could have expected from the Wilderneſs <hi>Iſa,</hi> 5. 1,—4. Hence that chide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtinging Interrogation, implying great diſappointment of juſt expectation in himſelf (the Lord ſpeaking there after the manner of men) and unreaſonable, unaccountable Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in them <hi>ver. 4. Wherefore when I looked it ſhould bring forth Grapes, brought it forth wild grapes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We that have all the Precious and Pleaſant things of God's Houſe afforded, and at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time continued when it is not ſo with others, are better dealt with, and at a Thouſand times more chargeable rate maintained than they; if our Returns be not ſomewhat ſingular, we ſhall never be able to hold up our Heads whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God ſhall thus interrogate us as he did them, and if he ſhould <hi>take away our Hedge and break down our ſtone wall, and leave us to be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en up and trodden down,</hi> and <hi>forbid the clouds to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon us</hi> ſo that in the Iſſue we be <hi>laid waſte</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he adds <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 6. If he ſhould <hi>take away the Vineyard from us, and let it out unto others that ſhould render him the fruit in their ſeaſons</hi> as <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 41. and when he had done all this, refer the matter to our own Judgment as he did to theirs <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5. 3. our Conſciences would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40711:38"/>
us to ſay <hi>Righteous art thou O Lord.</hi> God was angry with <hi>Hezekiah</hi> not becauſe he made no Returns at all (that ſanctifying Grace he had in him would not let him be altogether unthankful) but it's ſaid <hi>Hezekiah rendered not</hi>—According <hi>to the benefits done,</hi> and hence was Wrath upon him 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. 25. His Returns were not according to Expectation ſo proportionable to his Receivings as they might have been, and there lay the Controverſy. We wrong and reflect upon the Name and Houſe of God and the priviledges we enjoy there, under ſo many <hi>better dayes</hi> and <hi>better things</hi> for want of <hi>better</hi> Converſations, with which tho the Lord may bear long, he wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not alwaies.</p>
            <p>USE. 2. By way of Reproof</p>
            <p>If One day in God's Houſe be worth a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, then they are blame-worthy who in their Judgement or practice, or both, are guilty of Slighting, Undervalueing or Neglecting the ſame, and what is lightly eſteemed will be neglected. Now theſe are faulty, not only for wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of due reſpect to an <hi>Inſtitution of God</hi> or <hi>inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted Worſhip</hi> (which ought alwaies to be obſerved with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Veneration, as that about which the Lord is wont more eſpecially to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> jealous God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) but they are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40711:38"/>
to be reproved from the <hi>Text</hi> under that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as not conſulting their own intereſt, while they put a ſlight upon that wherein their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Profit &amp; Advantage is concerned, herein they miſs it in not doing well for themſelves.</p>
            <p>And here we may take notice either of a Total (or at leaſt very frequent) Neglect in ſome, ſo as not to come at all, or if they do its very rarely; or elſe when they do come it is not in ſuch a manner as they would if they believed there were ſuch profit there. Non-Attendance, rare-Attendance, ſuperficial and ſlighty Attendance are all of them very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable and unbecoming ſuch a place and ſuch Ordinances.</p>
            <p>There are ſome whom you ſhall ſeldom ſee at a Sermon, at leaſt upon a Lecture day, are ſtrangers to the Houſe of God, I cannot ſay do not <hi>know,</hi> but may ſay are very rarely <hi>found in</hi> the way thither. A moſt unworthy thing! that God ſhould ſet up an Houſe among us, and promiſe to afford us his Preſence, and give us a meeting there, and men cann't find in their Hearts to wait on him at the Time and Place appointed. That God ſhould make ſuch preparation for us in his Houſe, and ſend to invite us, and tell us he will make us very wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come there to the beſt he has, and that he is there waiting to entertain us and be gracious
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40711:39"/>
to us, and any ſhould ſend him that Anſwer that they have no mind to come, or if they do come, it is in ſuch a manner (which the heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearching and all-ſeeing God obſerves) as does declare that their whole heart is not in the work.</p>
            <p>To ſee the High-way to the Houſe of God mourn in <hi>a day of Contradiction</hi> and <hi>treading down in the valley of Viſion</hi> becauſe men are through Perſecution by an Hand of Violence hindred from walking therein, is a great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, &amp; matter of ſore Lamentation; but to ſee the High-way thither mourn in a time of Liberty and Encouragement, either becauſe when they may they will not walk therein, or if they do, it is with much Formality <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Indifferency, this is much more a Lamentation as being the great ſin and provocation of the Lords Sons and Daughters. When the way is blockt up by Perſecution it is but the <hi>Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of Profeſſors (tho' the ſin of Perſecutors) but their own declining when the way is open is the great <hi>ſin</hi> of Profeſſors. If when God ſets and holds open the doors of his Houſe (which are the Gate of Heaven) they put away Eternal life from themſelves, that is far worſe than to have others keep them off from it, and the meanes of attaining it. For them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs to bid God depart from them is a ſorer evil than for others to bid them depart from God.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40711:39"/>
And indeed ſuch do as it were ſay concerning God, he may be gone from them if he will, they care not for the Knowledge of his wayes, nor do they deſire to ſee or be acquainted with him.</p>
            <p>Some do this out of Opinion, pretending to have found a better Rule and greater <hi>light within,</hi> and thereupon deſpiſe external Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, lay them aſide as things beneath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, calling them <hi>Forms</hi> which perſons of their. Attainments have no need of, tho' it is much to be doubted that while they caſt off In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Forms (there is a Form of <hi>wholeſome Words,</hi> and a Form of <hi>wholſome Worſhip</hi> alſo) they leave themſelves <hi>without Form</hi> and (its to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> feared) will be found (as the ancient <hi>Chaos</hi> was) alſo <hi>void, and darkneſs over the faces of</hi> them too, notwithſtanding all their pretences to a more-than-ordinary Degree of Light<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe I ſhall ſay little at preſent, becauſe I preſume there are few or none here this day to hear me: Only this word or two <hi>viz.</hi> That is a falſe and unfreindly <hi>Light within</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaves men of the Light of the Word and help of Ordinances from <hi>without,</hi> from whence ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſouls have alwayes found (through the Concurrence of the Spirit) the greateſt Qnick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and ſafeſt Conduct. <hi>If the Light within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e darkneſs,</hi> (or lead men into darkneſs, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40711:40"/>
keep them out of thoſe wayes wherein they might meet with enlightening) <hi>how great is that darkneſs!</hi> It little availes to diſpute with men that are wiſe in their own eyes, and wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their own wayes; our beſt way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueing with ſuch is practical, <hi>viz.</hi> by ſo Prize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Valuing, Uſing the Ordinances of God's Houſe, as that our Proficiency <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> them and Benefit <hi>by</hi> them may be even in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences a Teſtimony <hi>for</hi> them, which will be wanting if we that uſe them live no better than they that uſe them not. This only I ſhall ſay that <hi>David</hi> (a man full of Light and Love) deſired that he might take a leaſe of the Houſe of God to dwell in for his Life-time <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. 4. And Chriſt pomiſed that in the way of Preaching &amp; Baptiſm (and by like reaſon all other Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of his Houſe) he would be with them to the end of the world; &amp; therefore the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to wait on him in ſuch Inſtitutions, and the promiſe of his preſence and Bleſſing upon ſo waiting concerns us in theſe daies, and will thoſe that ſhall ſucceed us ſo long as the world laſts. Know alſo that no Chriſtian is or ſhall be (really and according to Rule I mean, what ever he may through any miſtake cenceive) <hi>above</hi> Ordinances whilſt <hi>beneath</hi> Heaven.</p>
            <p>Others ſee no Glory in God's Houſe, find no Good, Get no profit thereby, and therefore
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40711:40"/>
neglect it, an Objection long agone made by them, and Anſwered by the Prophet <hi>Malachi Chapt.</hi> 3. ſomething has been already ſpoken thereunto, I ſhall add a few words more. Poſſibly their own experience may tel them ſo, they uſing Ordinances (when they did uſe them) with their wonted ſlightineſs and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality, found no profit in them, and thereupon gave over; laying the blame upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which was only juſtly chargeable upon their Formality and Hypocriſie in the uſe of the Ordinances.</p>
            <p>And here note that Chriſt himſelf gives that as the true Reaſon of their worſhiping God in vain <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 8, 9. not becauſe it was a vain thing to worſhip God, but becauſe they did not worſhip him in a right manner, they were Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and they did <hi>draw nigh him with their mouth and honour him with their lips but their heart was far from him,</hi> and therefore did they <hi>worſhip him in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in.</hi> It is no ſign that the Things in God's Houſe are not Good Things, beſt Things, yea a Thouſand times better than other things, becauſe they are not ſo to thee, No, no, it remains an everlaſting Truth that there are <hi>fat and marrowed Things</hi> in the Houſe of God, tho' they may ſeem to be dry, ſapleſs and unſavory Things unto thee. There is Divine Glory and Beauty <hi>there</hi> tho' thou ſee it not, and if it be hidden from thee
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40711:41"/>
thou mayſt with trembling Heart and Hands turn to the 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. and there read thy <hi>preſent</hi> Condition at leaſt (however God may in mercy enlighten thee <hi>afterwards) If our Goſpel be hid it is hid to them that are loſt.</hi> Thou goeſt up and down the world with the black mark of a <hi>loſt man</hi> upon thee. If that be true that <hi>God's word doeth Good to them that walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly</hi> Mic. 2. 7. what mayſt thou judge of thy ſelf to whom it does no good? Do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forbear to come becauſe thou haſt hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to found no profit, rather prepare thy ſelf ſo to come as that thou mayeſt find that profit which is there to be had, and which others have experienced.</p>
            <p>Some out of ſloth cannot endure to take pains to come, at leaſt if they are at any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Diſtance, or if there be any thing of Difficulty therein. A little Indiſpoſition of <hi>body</hi> (eſpecially if it meets with a great Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of <hi>ſpirit</hi>) ſhall be excuſe enough, and ſo a little unſeaſonableneſs of Weather<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. I know God <hi>will have mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> but let men beware they do not put a cheat upon themſelves: Self-deceivers are the worſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and that principally in ſuch momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous matters as theſe are. Sloth is full of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, and Liſtleſsneſs furniſhed with preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>A Sluggard is wiſer in his own conceit than ſeven men that can render a Reaſon.</hi> Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 26. 16.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40711:41"/>
Doe thus in thy outward Concerns and ſee if thou be not <hi>clothed with raggs</hi> Prov. 23. 21. Do not plow by reaſon of <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Cold, refuſe to ſow becauſe of the Wind, and to Reap from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Clouds, or to goe to Sea for fear of a Storm and try what will come of it. If tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excuſes ſhall keep men from the Houſe of God while they can run all Hazzards for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing their worldly Deſigns, think what God now <hi>does</hi> and an enlightned Conſcience one day <hi>will</hi> judge of ſuch a Frame.</p>
            <p>Others (if they would ſpeak it out, which for ſhame they dare not in words, tho' their practice ſpeaks it loud enough) love vain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, Drinking, Gameing, &amp;c. better than a Sermon. Alas for the Atheiſtical blindneſs and bruitiſh Senſuality that appears in ſuch an Humour! Is any Company better than that of God Father Son and Spirit? is any Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the world like the Communion of Saints? Any drink like the wine and milk and Water of Life that is here freely offered to thee? Is there any <hi>Game</hi> ſo pleaſing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable as that <hi>Work</hi> whereby thou mayſt win Chriſt? Is there not more refreſhment and Sweetneſs in a Sermon than in a Napp? Propound theſe and ſuch like Queſtions ſeri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſly to thy ſelf, and then ſee if thine own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience will not be thy Reprover and Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:40711:42"/>Some plead Buſineſs, Farmes and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, they have many things to doe and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tend to hear the Word of God. We have ſpoken ſomething to this Objection already, and therefore ſhall paſs it briefly now. Only conſider, If a King or chief Ruler ſhould come to our Town, and ſend for us immediatly to come before him, &amp; we ſhould ſend him word we could not tend to come, think how he would take it; eſpecially if he aſſured us that he came out of great kindneſs &amp; reſpect to us and that he had great preferment &amp; gifts to beſtow upon us, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſour for us out of good will, and that our waiting upon him ſhould be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakably to our ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, how ſhould we befool our ſelves for loſing ſuch an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty! Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo it is, and infinitly more than ſo. It would be dreadful if it ſhould be any man's lott under the Goſpel to be damned becauſe he could not tend to be ſaved, and yet undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the caſe of many who will ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly periſh becauſe they could not ſpare the Time from their ſecular affairs and ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al pleaſures <hi>to work out their own Salvation</hi> by induſtrious applying themſelves to the Uſe of all means that God has appointed for the ſame. The promiſe in the Text of the getting the good of a Thouſand dayes in one does fully anſwer the Objection, and leave no room for an excuſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:40711:42"/>If a man that were gathering of chips or picking up ſtraws ſhould ſay he were ſo buiſie that he could not afford the Time to come and receive his loading of Gold and Jewels which he might have for the fetching, we ſhould ſay of him he were <hi>penny wiſe and pound fooliſh.</hi> If you do not believe the Word of God is better than Thouſands of Silver and Gold, what doe you with your Bibles? why do you hear and read ſuch Books, that ye account full of Fables and Untruths? If they be true why do you not act accordingly? you muſt deny the Scriptures or you muſt value and attend upon the Word preached.</p>
            <p>You ſay you would come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut your world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs will not ſuffer you; it ſeems then that if you had a proſpect of worldly Profit before you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou would put in for a ſhare. And I verily believe that if every perſon in Town might be well aſſured of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Ten or Twenty ſhillings a day that comes to Lecture, and were preſent before it began, continued till all the Service were over, and kept wakeing all the Time too, the money to be paid him as ſoon as he went out of the door, we ſhould have our Houſes crammed and Seats crouded, every vacant corner filled, you ſhould ſcarce find a man
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40711:43"/>
in the ſtreets, nor Taverns, nor private houſes, nor would men have their Children or ſervants to play or work at home, if there were ſuch Gain to be gotten in two houres time here. Now what a low, earthly ſpirit doth this diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and how unkindly muſt Chriſt needs take it to have his Houſe and Ordinances thus baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undervalued! ſhould not men's Greedineſs of worldly Gain and Intenſeneſs thereabout convince them of this Duty?</p>
            <p>You open your Shops every day, you <hi>riſe in the morning</hi> (or ſhould do <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 22, 23.) <hi>and go to your labour until the evening;</hi> you go to '<hi>Change</hi> every day, and obſerve your hours there to meet and confer about your Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to enquire Newes, diſcourſe of Affairs and diſpatch Buſineſs, and ſurely your Buſineſs for Heaven deſerves as much Time and Thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
            <p>And it heightens the matter of Reproof when men will not only not come to a Sermon, but ſit in their ſhops (perhaps in a worſe place) and that in view of the place of Worſhip, will be walking the ſtreets, and driving their Teams to and fro juſt by the Meeting-houſe ſide, and that in the ſight of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that are aſſembled to worſhip God, to the great diſhonour of God and Grief of tender
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40711:43"/>
Conſciences: ſurely it is not a Thing comely nor of good Report, (and ſuch things we ought to follow <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 8.) This caſts a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon our Worſhip in the ſight of the Heathen among whom we dwell, it puts a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low eſteem upon it, and is matter of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal unto the prophane &amp; carnal ones, who are hardned in their evil way and confirmed in their Atheiſtical Opinions about God and his Worſhip, when they ſee us who profeſs higher to carry it with ſuch unſeemlineſs and diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect toward the ſame.</p>
            <p>If there were <hi>no open viſion</hi> among us the Word would be <hi>more precious</hi> as it was with them 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 1. If the Enemy were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and the water (yea and bread too) of Bethlehem we ſhould <hi>long</hi> more for it, and take more pains after it. But the Word is <hi>commonly</hi> preached and ſo <hi>lightly</hi> eſteemed, <hi>eaſie to be had</hi> and therefore <hi>low</hi>-prized. So was the Manna (tho' Angels food) when rained about the Camp <hi>every</hi> day, and called <hi>light Manna.</hi> The Lord grant that our making ſo light of it may not provoke Him to ſend a Famine of Hearing the Word among us <hi>Amos</hi> 8. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> I know what ſome will object here Viz. that <hi>I lay more ſtreſs upon Lectures than is due, and urge the Attending them with more ſtrictneſs than is neceſſary, are they not to attend their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40711:44"/>
Callings diligently and laboriouſly? do they not ſerve God there as well as in their General Calling? what, may they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot upon any account miſs a Lecture &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Do I ſay more than my Text ſaith? <hi>One day is better than a Thouſand,</hi> and is not Time beſt ſpent where there is ſuch odds in point of profit? will not Prudence direct every man to doe the beſt he can for his own beſt Advantage? I know there may be juſt reaſon to abſent from a Lecture, as the Caſe may <hi>be,</hi> and would not therefore make that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary which God, hath not made ſo. All that I would i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that men beware they deal not deceitfully with God nor fallaciouſly with themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es by alledging that for a Cauſe which is not ſo, and will not paſs with <hi>God</hi> for a Cauſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow,</hi> nor with <hi>their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Conference when it comes to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Let all men in theſe matters ſo deal as becomes thoſe that make the Knowledge of God in Chriſt their <hi>Life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal,</hi> Communion and Fellowſhip with Him in all the wayes of his appointment their <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi> that have ſubordinated all other things to his <hi>Glory,</hi> and made Dwelling in his Houſe their <hi>one thing:</hi> and ſo as they may practical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrate that they do unfeignedly believe and realize the Truth of this Text.</p>
            <p>Let them ſee that under any pretenſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they do not gratifie a profane, Atheiſtical,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40711:44"/>
ſenſual or covetous ſpirit in themſelves, nor juſtly grieve the good Spirit of God in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or others. Be ſure that the Houſe of God and the Concerns thereof have in our Hearts (and let it alſo be manifeſt in our Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions) a deſerved precedence before our own houſes and the Affairs thereof. So live, ſo act as that it may be evident that God's Worſhip has the preeminence with us. Keep up the Honour of his Houſe by longing and panting for it, and rejoycing in heart when it ſhall be ſaid to us <hi>Come let us goe up thither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do but ſhew ſuch an Affection <hi>to</hi> and Delight in God's Houſe as God's people have been all along Characteriſed by, and our Souls good and Edification may be promoted by, and that is the ſumme of what is intended by this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and with any thing leſſe than this we ſhall not be able to approve our ſelves to the Heart-ſearching God that we do truly, cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>love the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of his Houſe and the plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> where his Honour dwells Pſal.</hi> 26. 8.</p>
            <p>Furth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, here alſo are to be reproved thoſe that if they do come, they come with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies only without their Hearts, let their Hearts run after their Covetouſneſs while with their Bodies they ſit like God's people: Such doe the Work of the <hi>Lord</hi> deceitfully and <hi>their own</hi> unprofitably.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:40711:45"/>Such heartleſs (however they may ſeem ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) Services will not excuſe them from that Denunciation and Curſe of <hi>Deceivers Mal.</hi> 1. 14. who <hi>have a Male in the Flock but ſacrifice a corrupt thing.</hi> The Excellent things that are there deſervedly call for all the Soul, Heart, Mind and might to be imployed thereabout, and the contrary is very fooliſh and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>If one day in the Houſe of God be worth a Thouſand</hi> they may not paſs without Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion who for want of Care and Heed loſe any part of this precious Time by <hi>coming late,</hi> after that ſo profitable Worſhip of God is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. Did men indeed beleeve and conſider that there is ſo much good to be gotten, the Conſideration of the profit ſhould make every one ſtrive to be foremoſt, to be at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſo good an Exerciſe. <hi>We are all here preſent before God</hi> well became thoſe Hearers <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 33. and they got well by their ready At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt fell on all them that heard the Word</hi> ver. 44. To be <hi>watching and waiting at Wiſdom's gates and poſts</hi> has a Bleſſing promiſed <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. 34. Not to be at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a Sermon is a great diſadvantage to him that makes Information and Edification his Buſineſs: And to be abſent from the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before the Sermon is to miſs an Ordinance that ſits us for Hearing; and by which the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40711:45"/>
Word heard comes to be <hi>ſanctified</hi> to us. If the Whole be ſo good, he <hi>conſults ill</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that loſes any part of it.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Sleeping at a Sermon</hi> is hereby condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the worth of a Day or an Hour in God's Houſe affords matter of ſharp Reproof to them that can ſleep away any part of it. <hi>What can you not watch with</hi> Chriſt <hi>one hour?.</hi> Men do not uſe to ſleep when they are receiving mony. A man that is ſtanding before the Judge while the Sentence of Abſolution or Condemnation is pronouncing will certainly keep his eyes open; why, of no leſs importance is our being at a Sermon, where we are before God the Judge of all, and hearing thoſe words by which we ſhall be judged at the Laſt day. How they can be ſaid to <hi>take heed how they hear</hi> who hear themſelves aſleep, would be good for them to conſider when they are awake, and might help to keep them ſo. They that ſleep out a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon will be like the barren Heath of the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs <hi>that does not ſee when good comes.</hi> And it is to be feared that he has but little ſenſe of the Worth of that Ordinance or expectation of benefit by it that can allow himſelf in ſuch a Deportment under it; a due Eſteem of it, with ſuitable Expectation from it would teach him better. Sitting aſleep while <hi>the words of eternal life</hi> are diſpenſing is not <hi>Sitting like God's people.</hi> Men may be awake and yet little the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40711:46"/>
better, but they may conclude that what time was ſlept away was loſt Time. He that gazes or ſleeps away ſome few Sentences, may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by incapacitate himſelf for underſtanding the whole Diſcourſe. However, poſſibly that word may then be a ſpeaking which would have ſuited thy caſe and reached thy Heart if thou hadſt been awake to hear it, and ſuch a vvord it may be thou ſhalt never have an opportuiny of hearing again. You have or may have in your hands <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Mather's <hi>Sermon upon Act.</hi> 20. 9.</note> an awakning Diſcourſe of God's exemplary Juſtice upon ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> God may doe ſo by thee, when he finds thee in a deep ſleep at a Sermon, he may make it a dead-ſleep to thee, and may ſufficiently vindicate himſelf by rendring that Reaſon <hi>I will be ſanctified in them that come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh me, and before all the people I will be glori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> Levit. 10. 3. How that Word ſhould prove a <hi>Savour of life</hi> to thee which thou didſt ſleep at the hearing of I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine, and if not a Savour of life, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is not like to be <hi>a Savour of death,</hi> do thou conſider. Did you ever hear of a poor indigent perſon, that being ſent for by ſome great rich man to receive ſome bountiful, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Dole at his hands fell faſt aſleep while take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no, the Hopes of a ſmall Alms will make a man w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h and look.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:40711:46"/>Again thoſe that are quite tired if the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon exceed ſomewhat the uſual length, and inwardly think if they do not openly ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>what a wearineſs is it!</hi> Such do not carry as if they believed and realized this Text.</p>
            <p>If you were brought to an heap of Gold and licenſed for an hours time to tell it over, and were ſo have for your own as much as you could tell, you would not think the Glaſs too long, nor account your ſelves wronged if permitted to take part of another Glaſs, nay a whole one; is not God's word better than Thouſands of ſilver and Gold? Can you ſit hour after hour in vain Company drinking and telling ſtories and never think the time long, and is a Sermon too long for you? I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a Solemn Word once delivered by that great man of God, now with God, Mr. <hi>Richard Mather, You</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that think the Time long at a Sermon, will think the Time long in Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hence it is <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe men are weary, they cannot ſtay till Sermon be ended, or at leaſt with-draw before the prayer after Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the Bleſſing in the cloſe of all. Does this become thoſe that think one day in God's Houſe worth a Thouſand? Is Chriſt ſpeaking to you, and have you not the patience to hear him out? Has Chriſt procured a liberty for us to come before God and ſay <hi>all</hi> that we
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40711:47"/>
have to ſay (which is the import of the <hi>Greek</hi> word <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 16.) and ſhall we reckon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to hear <hi>part</hi> of what he has to ſay? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that becauſe he ſpeaks and we regard not, he do not retaliate to us accordingly, that we ſhould ſpeak and call and cry, and he not regard or hear us. Remember the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Example <hi>Act. 10. Cornelius and</hi> his Company were not only got together and wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the coming of <hi>Peter</hi> ver. 24. But they lookt at themſelves as Aſſembled before God, and their Buſineſs was to hear <hi>all</hi> that the Lord had commanded to be ſpoken.</p>
            <p>It is a great ſlight put upon a Friend that out of compaſſion to us, ſeeing us in a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous condition has ſtudied a way for our Relief, and is very ſeriouſly diſcourſing us thereabout, and we tell him he muſt cut ſhort or elſe we muſt be gone, and in the Iſſue goe away before he has done. If a man ſhould be telling a tale of more than an hour long, eſpecially if there be any thing of Wit and pleaſure in it, you cann't chuſe but hear out his ſtory; and if a by-ſtander ſhould add a parallel as much longer many perſons would hardly get away till he vvere gotten to the further end of it. Does not a Diſcourſe of God and Chriſt and thy great Salvation, deſerve the beſt of thy Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            <p>Or if men make a ſhift (and an hard ſhift
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40711:47"/>
it is through their uneaſineſs and wearineſs) to ſtay till the Sermon be ended, then what tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling out of the Meeting-houſe, as if it had been a Priſon to them, and they were glad of a <hi>Goal-delivery!</hi> what clattering and noiſe, to the great diſturbance of thoſe that fain would but by your meanes cannot joyn in the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Exerciſe!</p>
            <p>To ſuch let me ſay, What have you no need of a prayer after Sermon that God would write in your hearts what hath been ſounding in your ears? Does not God deſerve to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and praiſed for the liberty of a Sermon, and do not your ſouls need a prayer to him that alone is able to teach you to profit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that his labour in ſpeaking and yours in hearing may not be in vain? And in ſpecial how dare you turn your backs upon the Bleſſing, has the Lord appointed &amp; Authorized his Miniſters to bleſs you in his Name, and are you in ſo much haſt that you cannot ſtay to hear it and ſhare in it? Beware leſt God ſay of you (as of him <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. 17.) becauſe you delighted not in Bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo let-it be far from you. Why the good of all you have done depends upon a Bleſſing, and can you be content to goe away without that?</p>
            <p>See what a great Thing the Lord makes of the Prieſt's pronouncing a Bleſſing <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. 22. to 28. <hi>On this wiſe ſhall you bleſs the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40711:48"/>
of Iſrael ſaying &amp;c.</hi> and after the Bleſſing adds, <hi>They ſhall put my Name upon them and I will bleſs them.</hi> Note alſo how Solomon in that great Solemnity 1. <hi>King</hi> 8. and after prayer <hi>ſtood. and bleſt—the Congregation,</hi> and it's ſaid he bleſſed <hi>all</hi> the Congregation, then they did not croud out as ſoon as the prayer was ended, but they <hi>all</hi> ſtayed to hear and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the ſame, and it was worth their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. To be commended to the Grace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove and Fellowſhip of God Father Son and Spirit is certainly worth the ſtaying for, and that minute while you are waiting for and receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bleſſing will bring them a Thouſand times more profit than thoſe that ſlight and neglect the bleſſing uſually get the while.</p>
            <p>Let me further ask ſuch perſons</p>
            <p>What come you to the Houſe of God for? what was your Errand thither? and have you got that you came for, that makes you with-draw before the Worſhip of God be finiſhied? Did you come to draw near to God, to ſee his <hi>goings in the ſanctuary,</hi> and to have Fellowſhip with him there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> did you ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that one day in God's Houſe is worth a Thouſand, and have you found it ſo? why ſo weary then, why in ſuch Haſt to be gone? thoſe that have met with ſome Taſts would be for more, if the Beginning was ſweet you
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40711:48"/>
would have ſtayed to the latter end. He that comes for Chriſt to an Ordinance, whether he meet him or meet him not at his Entrance thereupon, he will ſtay by it; if he meet him, the ſweetneſs of the enjoyment will detain him, if he meet him not, the hopes that he may enjoy him will keep him waiting. If Chriſt appear to him in his glory, he will ſay it is good being here, if Chriſt as yet appear not, he will account it worth his Labour to continue his attendance in expectation that he may. The ſincere ſeeker cannot be ſatisfied without finding, the true finder will think he hath never found enough, and therefore will not goe away ſo long as there is any hope of finding more. He will ſay with himſelf, who can tell but the laſt word in the Sermon, the laſt clauſe in the prayer, or the Bleſſing in the cloſe of the whole may be intended by God as a ſpecial Bleſſing to mee? and accordingly during the whole time of the Duty will keep himſelf in the way of the Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Again if any ſhould come to Meeting only for a name, to get and keep a Reputation for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, truly if you think you have made your market and done your errand I doubt you will find your ſelves miſtaken; ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and unſeaſonable With-drawing will crack your Credit and leſſen your Eſteem among
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40711:49"/>
them that are ſerious and judicious.</p>
            <p>They are to be Reproved who tho' they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to much Devotion, come to the Houſe of God and <hi>ſit there like Gods people,</hi> yet while they offer <hi>the lame and the blind</hi> unto God, reſerving <hi>the Male in the flock</hi> for their better friends, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Inſincerity unto the Heart-Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, who curſes ſuch deceivers (<hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 14.) however cunningly and fairly they may carry it before men. The Lord tells the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> Cap. 33. 31. what a ſort of Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers he had, who both look'd and ſate, ſpoke and in their outward behavior carried it like his people, <hi>but their Hearts went after their Co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vetouſneſs.</hi> Their Hearts were in their Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Fields, Shops, in cloſe purſuit of their worldly Concerns under the Cloak of Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Worſhip. God expects the Heart, if we give him not that, he reckons he hath nothing; if he has the Heart he can overlook many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and Defects, while the moſt ſpecious Appearances and faireſt Performances without the Heart, are but bodily exerciſe and Lip-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, little profitable to themſelves, but high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoking unto God. Such Perſons give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od only the Skin for the Sacrifice, the lame, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an, ſeeming Services inſtead of the fat of heart-Obedience, and the Lord gives them as good as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bring, rewarding empty Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40711:49"/>
with as empty Expectations. They are deceived that think God will be mocked; he doth not only ſee men, but ſee into men and through them, and all thoſe duties will be found too light for his acceptance that have not the heart going with them in the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>It was a pleaſant ſight <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 1. to ſee the people crowding together to hear the Word of God, inſomuch that they trod one upon another (and one would think it ſhould be common among us where the people are ſo numerous, and the acceſs to the Ordinances ſo eaſie) but yet even then it is obſervable that Chriſt began with a caution againſt Hypocriſie. [<hi>Beware of Hypocriſie</hi>] is a Text fit to be preach'd on before the moſt zealous and full Auditory. Look diligently that the ſnake of Hypocriſie lurk not, lye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not hid among the talleſt and rankeſt herbs of a forward Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Worſhiping of God and coming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly to his Houſe is like the Apothecaries Oyntment, very odoriferous and grateful, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the dead Fly of Hypocriſie will ſpoil the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of it, and make us to loſe all that we have wrought thereabout.</p>
            <p>USE 3. In the laſt place this Doctrine may be improved by way of Exhortation, and we are from hence excited unto theſe three Duties,</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:40711:50"/>
               <item>I. To Prize the Houſe of God after the ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> given in the Text.</item>
               <item>II. That we thereupon carefully attend the ſame, and this will follow on the former.</item>
               <item>III. That we ſo carry it towards and under thoſe Ordinances as that we may find the Truth of this Text in our own Experience, which is the genuine fruit of our being ſincere in the two foregoing duties.</item>
            </list>
            <p>1. Thus prize the Liberties and Priviledges of God's Houſe, labour to believe that <hi>One day in God's Horſe is worth a Thouſand,</hi> in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou wilt ſhew a <hi>David</hi>-like heart, an heart after God's own Heart. Indeed <hi>David</hi> was taught the <hi>worth</hi> by the <hi>want</hi> of God's Houſe: the Lord grant we may learn at a cheaper rate, uſually our Dullneſs puts him upon ſuch kind of Diſcipline. We may well and ſafely take them at the price God has ſet them, they are not prized too high.</p>
            <p>2. So prizing the Houſe of God, attend it accordingly, Here is moſt profit to be had and therefore omit no ſeaſon of being here, Wait dayly at Wiſdom's poſts. You may buy Gold too dear, but the Liberties of God's Houſe you cannot buy to dear, their <hi>fruit is better than Gold,</hi> and their <hi>Reven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e than choice Silver, Prov.</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:40711:50"/>
8. 19. with 34. Tho' you ſhould be at great p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines and expence you will have a good Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niworth.</p>
            <p>Let not any Ordinary Buſineſs divert you from a Sermon. Make Conſcience of taking every Opportunity to work while the Day laſts.</p>
            <p>And here let me ſay, If <hi>that</hi> Buſineſs hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers you from a Sermon that would not hinder you from a Feaſt, a merry-meeting, from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving mony, from ſpending an hour or two with a friend that had ſent for you, or come to viſit you, from making a good Bargain &amp;c. I ſay if kept from a Sermon by thoſe occaſions which would not have kept you from <hi>theſe,</hi> you will not be able to anſwer it to God nor to your own Judgment and Conſciences neither, when they come to be Serious and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate.</p>
            <p>Then call upon one another, exhort and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage one another, ſay <hi>come let us goe to the Houſe of God,</hi> you that have ever taſted the ſweet of God's Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been made joyful in his Houſe of Prayer tell others what you have found, your Example and Council may be of uſe to draw others along with you, for which <hi>they</hi> will thank you, and <hi>God</hi> will reward you another day.</p>
            <p>3. So attend upon God in his Houſe as that your own Experience may teſtifie to the Truth
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40711:51"/>
of this Text and Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> That One day here is worth a Thouſand, that you may be able to ſay as we have heard, ſo have we ſeen in the Houſe of God, we have heard that there is great profit and Gain there to be gotten, and we have found it ſo. Do not content your ſelves (as many do) that you have been there, but enquire what you have done and gotten there. To goe in a Round of Duties, Secret, Private, Publique without making any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs or getting any profit, is in it ſelf irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and unto God very provoking. You are going up to the Houſe of God to ſpend a day before him there, now ſee that it prove a good day to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that you may have the good of it to your ſelves, this ought to be every one's Care.</p>
            <p>You would think your ſelves much to blame if being in extream Want you ſhould come to a plentiful market where all manner of ſupplies are offered you freely, and you carry home no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with you: And yet how often hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny an Hearer come into God's Houſe and tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried till the Sermon was ended, but carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way not one penniworth of ſpiritual good, ſoul-benefit, and it may be not ſo much as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted or troubled to think on it.</p>
            <p>How did the Spouſe behave her ſelf when her Beloved was with-drawn (<hi>Cant.</hi> 3. 1, to 5. ſhe riſes, goes about, ſeeks, enquires of the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40711:51"/>
Watch-men, never reſts till ſhe had found him, and then held him faſt and brought him home with her. 'Tis Finding Chriſt in his Houſe that is the profit of our day's work, that renders Time ſo advantagiouſly ſpent, and therefore this ſhould be ſincerely aym'd at, and ſtrenuouſly endeavoured by every one that comes thither. This was <hi>Mary</hi>'s Caſe <hi>Joh.</hi> 20. 1,—16. ſhe got up early and her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was not to ſee the Sepulchre where Jeſus was laid, or the linnen Clothes and Napkins in which he was wrapt, but to ſee Jeſus himſelf, <hi>her Lord</hi> was in her heart, and to ſee Him was her Errand, hence when others went away with no other ſight than the Grave and linnen, ſhe waits and weeps and looking into the Grave there ſees Angels, unto whom ſhe gives this reaſon of her weeping becauſe her Lord was carried away, and turning about enquired of the ſuppoſed Gardener for her <hi>Lord,</hi> and being thus earneſt and unſatisfied in her Enquiries at laſt ſhe found him.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhould every one behave himſelf having realized to himſelf that the Ordinances of God's Houſe are wayes of Communion with Chriſt and that <hi>there</hi> lies the good of them, he ſhould make that his buſines and be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with nothing unleſs he attains his end: It ſhould not ſatisfie him that he hath been at the place where Chriſt is wont to appear, and that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40711:52"/>
he hath been at the place where Chriſt is wont to appear, and that he hath been under Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in which Jeſus Chriſt is wont to be conveied, but he muſt goe and wait with an heart fixt for Chriſt himſelf, and ſadly bemoan himſelf under a diſappointment there, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch the Lord will make good that word <hi>Iſa. 45. 19. I ſaid not to the ſeed of Jacob ſeek ye my face in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In no Duties is the Word of God more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn than about thoſe of his Houſe. See the dreadful charge to him that preaches 1. <hi>Tim. 6. 13. I give th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e charge in the ſight of God who quickeneth all things, and before Jeſus Chriſt &amp;c.</hi> So again 2. <hi>Tim. 4. 1, 2. I charge thee before God and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and his Kingdom, Preach the Word, be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon &amp;c.</hi> In obedience to which Command are Lectures ſet up; and can you think that you which <hi>hear</hi> are not under a like Charge? Shall they that preach be ſo charged to preach &amp; <hi>ſo</hi> preach as in the ſight of him that will judge them for their preaching, and may you that are to hear think to ſcape the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God if you hear without Seriouſneſs and Profit? Does not his <hi>Strictneſs</hi> with them that <hi>preach,</hi> more than intimate that he will alſo be <hi>exact</hi> with them that <hi>hear?</hi> If they muſt take heed to themſelves and their Doctrine,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40711:52"/>
you muſt take heed to your ſelves and your Hearing. If they muſt ſpeak ſo for matter, and manner, and end, as they that look to anſwer it at the great and dreadful Day; you muſt hear upon the like peril.</p>
            <p>There is no ſerious preacher of the Goſpel but goes with an akeing heart about his work, and when he has preached is ready to condemn himſelf for fear leſt he hath not ſo ſpoken as he ought to have ſpoken; and I believe that there is no ſerious Hearer but will ſee cauſe to ask himſelf, and have I ſo heard as I ought to have heard?</p>
            <p>Let us pray for <hi>David</hi> ſpirit, Affection and Experience, of which there is but little now a dayes to be found.</p>
            <p>Take a few Directions.</p>
            <p>1. Be well acquainted with the Being, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Worth, and Need of your ſouls.</p>
            <p>Know that you have ſouls, how many live as if they had none? Conſider alſo they are immortal Exiſtences and muſt live for ever. Then acquaint your ſelves with their Needs, liſten to their Cravings, and think of what a neceſſity they are in of a Supply.</p>
            <p>Your ſouls are a Thouſand times better than your bodies, and therefore Providing for them of a Thouſand times more Concernment.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40711:53"/>
Oh, an immortal Soul, eternal Eſtate, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Life are momentous Conſiderations, and ſhould be attended accordingly.</p>
            <p>2. This being ſuppoſed, it will neceſſarily follow that you are indiſpenſibly bound to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend all meanes that God has appointed for the Salvation of your Souls. Neglecting means for outward Subſiſtence, or bodily Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance will bring you to Penury; then neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting meanes for your ſoul's maintenance will iſſue in Ruin and Miſery.</p>
            <p>3. Preſs on your ſouls the ſtamp of Divine Authority that is upon the Ordinances of his Houſe. Here God will be found, &amp; if you ſlight theſe wayes of his appointing, he will not be found elſewhere. And be aſſured that God will not deceive you. Here, he hath recorded his Name, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you wait here, you wait un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Promiſe of a bleſſing, and ſhall not wait for nothing.</p>
            <p>Then come to the Houſe of God out of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, not out of Cuſtom, nor for any by-Ends, and if you come conſcientiouſly, you will come conſtantly, I mean as often as God gives you an opportunity.</p>
            <p>To omit one Duty does but make way for our omitting another. Once give way to Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40711:53"/>
and you will never be without them, but they will come in upon you like 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od: Make but a Gap once, and you will ſcarce know how or when to ſtop it. And who can tel but <hi>that</hi> ſeaſon which you loſe might have been for your Everlaſting Advantage? The diſeaſed perſons not knowing when the Angel would come down and move the waters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay there alwayes waiting to prevent the loſs of an opportunity; and ſo ſhould we.</p>
            <p>A pious ſoul if providentially detained from God's Houſe growes the more hungry after it, the want of one meal ſharpens his ſtomach and increaſes his Appetite for the next; but a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al heart who out of ſloth and ſlightineſs neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects it, will grow every day more carleſs and unconcern'd than other, like a weak ſtomach, the more it faſts the more it may.</p>
            <p>4. Get ſuitable preparations for ſuch a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity. When <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was commanded by God to goe to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to worſhip, he adviſes his people to <hi>put away the ſtrange Gods, waſh their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Gen. 35. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 3. Every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſines of moment and Importance beſpeaks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reparation. A Journy by land, a Voyage by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, Entertainment of a great friend call for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reparation; much more then when our work to meet with and entertain the Lord of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at his Houſe which is appointed for a place
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40711:54"/>
of meeting with God <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 23. Hence that charge <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5. 1. <hi>Keep thy foot when thou goeſt to the houſe of God, and be more ready to hear &amp;c.</hi> When there we muſt be ready, then there muſt be ſome time taken to make ready, and that on penalty of <hi>offering the ſacrifices of fools.</hi> He that has ſo great a work to do, and does not prepare for it, does egregiouſly play the fool. They that obſerve their own Hearts will find that they are not ordinarily ſo ready for ſo great a work of <hi>drawing near to God</hi> as they ought to be; then either we muſt prepare, or ruſh in without preparation, and what ill muſick muſt that needs be in God's ear where the Inſtrument is out of tune? the danger of which we had better believe and prevent than experience.</p>
            <p>6. Goe thither with anſwerable Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no better in the Houſe God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we expect no better. Ayming too low is the way to miſs the mark. If after humble Preparation our hearts are big with Exqecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Lord will not ſuffer our Hopes to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abortive. <hi>The expectation of the poor ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> Pſal. 9. 18. Such profit as you have heard of is to be had in God's Houſe, believe it, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for it, carry your empty veſſels, open your mouthes wide, expect to have them filled and they ſhall be filled. Look what you need and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40711:54"/>
God promiſes, and you ſhall not look in vain.</p>
            <p>7. Let your attendance when there, be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to your expectations in going thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Serious Preparation and great Expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation will occaſion vigorous Attendance. To come with a ſence of great need to a place of full ſupply, with up-raiſed Expectations, will oblige a man to look diligently leſt he goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without his Errand.</p>
            <p>The ſervants of <hi>Benhadad</hi> (1. <hi>King.</hi> 20. 31, 32, 33.) ſaw what an ill caſe there maſter was in, &amp; had heard that <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Kings were merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, this gave them encouragement, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared themſelves accordingly, in the capacity of humble, periſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, ſelf-judging Suppliants, and in moſt ſubmaſſive Language preſented their Requeſt before <hi>Ahab,</hi> and then it's ſaid <hi>they did diligently deſerve whether any thing would come from him, and did haſtily catch it,</hi> and accordingly obtained their Deſire. Why know that we have far greater encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to wait upon God in his Houſe, we have an Invitation which they had not, we have a Promiſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon, wheras they went as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, upon and <hi>may be</hi> only: Our neceſſities alſo are greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not for the ſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> lives, but for preſervation of the lives of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls, that ſhould be ten Thouſand times more dear to us; then
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40711:55"/>
let us prepare thoroughly, come expectingly, and then attend diligently, and catch up every word greedily, withal waiting for the breathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit in an Ordinance, and we ſhall find that the King of Heaven is far more graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and bountiful than the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were merciful.</p>
            <p>8. Beware how you ſpend your Time after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. When men have been warmed in an Ordinance they had need ſee that they do not catch cold. Watching <hi>after</hi> Hearing is as needful as Watching <hi>unto</hi> Hearing. It's noted of the Thorny Hearers <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 14. that <hi>when they have heard they go forth, and are choakt with cares and riches and pleaſures.</hi> Many a precious Sermon is thus loſt. As they are like to get but little good by coming to the Houſe of God who come reaking out of their worldly occaſions without any prae-conſideration or preparation; ſo they are like to loſe or leſſen what they have got who ruſh into the world again without after-conſideration <hi>of</hi> or meditation <hi>on</hi> what they have mett with. The <hi>World</hi> was ever a great Enemy to the <hi>Word.</hi> Communing with our own Hearts and Diſcourſing one with another about what we have heard and ſeen in God's Houſe, will notably promote our profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency under the ſame.</p>
            <p>When the Lord ſpake ſo loud to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40711:55"/>
that dreadful Judgment of the turning the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Bloud, it is ſaid, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7. 23. that <hi>he turned and went into the houſe,</hi> and ſo it never went to his Heart. Had he not turned away his eyes <hi>from,</hi> but kept them fixed <hi>on</hi> that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn object, it might have reached his Heart. And thus often it proves; many a word, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a Conviction, many a good Beginning is loſt in the Houſe. From God's Houſe men turn into their own, and <hi>there</hi> in the Buſineſs of the Houſe, in the Cares and Pleaſures of the Houſe, in the Company of the Houſe, in the various Diverſions that they meet with there and elſewhere, all is loſt as tho' it had never been.</p>
            <p>By way of motive take A<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> few Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>1. Conſider whether thy own Judgement and Conſcience be not convicted of the Truth of this Doctrine. Doth not Conſcience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim aloud (or at leaſt ſecretly whiſper in thine ears) that all this is is true? Is not God better than the world, and Communion with him than any worldly Gain? And then is it not better for thee to lock up thy doores, ſhut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p thy ſhop, and goe to the Houſe of God in the ſeaſon of it, yea and carry thy people
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:40711:56"/>
with thee too, and if they gain thou wilt gain too, if they gain not thou ſhalt not loſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt done thy Duty. Now if thou art convinced, think how it will look in an evil day, to have gone on in the neglect of a duty of which thou haſt been convinced, eſpecially ſo profitable a duty as this. Thou mayſt poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly ſilence Conſcience for a while, but canſt not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, it will one day cry like a travailing wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and all the worldly Gain thou haſt gotten the while will not ſtop the mouth of it.</p>
            <p>2. Know that God will call us to a Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for all the Opportunities that we have had, and for all that we might have had, whether we took them or no. You ſhall be accountable not only for all the fer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons you <hi>have</hi> heard, but alſo for all thoſe that you <hi>might</hi> have heard, and nothing but a ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al, careleſs, vain, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Heart kept you from. Eſpecially you that have been idleing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing ſtill, drinking, ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp;c. the while; God will aſſuredly ſet you down in his Book Debitors for ſuch a Sermon, &amp; he will be ſure to reckon with you when the books come to be opened. Here is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion made, the Table f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your ſelves invited, your Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er laid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your portion car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out for you, and you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt pay whether you eat or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> then beſt to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and take your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, ſeeing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40711:56"/>
you muſt bear your part of the Loſs?</p>
            <p>3. Contempt of God's Houſe and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Ordinances of the ſame will be very griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and offenſive unto God, and ſuch neglect will be called Contempt.</p>
            <p>For God to ſet up his Houſe among us, and be at the charge of continuing to us the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the ſame, and yet for us to deſpiſe and under value them will be highly provoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Indeed it is a ſin that has all other ſins in it, or attending on it. No duty is well done if this be omitted: You cannot rightly ſerve God in your <hi>own</hi> Houſes if you do not while and when you may, at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d Him in <hi>his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. By this ſin we provoke the Lord to ſhut up the doores of his Houſe among us, to pluck up ſtakes and be gone from the midſt of us, If you refuſe to hear, God may juſtly refuſe to ſpeak. <hi>Ezel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be made dumb to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous people.</p>
            <p>Let us be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, God is threatening to break up Houſe among us, and if ever he ſo does, our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of his Houſe will be the cauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in God's Houſe which hath been hitherto leſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſeems to be ſhake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord looks as if he were de parting from us, there be many awful Symptom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:40711:57"/>
Symptoms of his Departure, and <hi>woe unto us if he. depart from us Hoſ.</hi> 9, 12.</p>
            <p>Our Father's Love to the Houſe of God above their own houſes and all outward Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, Occaſioned the bringing of his Tabern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle into this Wilderneſs; ſee that the coldneſs of our Affection thereto does not prevail with him to remove it again. There is a beginn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made among us already, <hi>Judgment is begun at the Houſe of God,</hi> let us take warning and receive Inſtruction. the maſter of the Houſe is riſen from his place, and hath begun to ſhut the door, and if men either care not to come in, or venture to come careleſly in, he will ſhutt it quite.</p>
            <p>New-England's Name and Glory has been <hi>Jehovah-Shammah</hi> [the Lord is there] His Houſe and Ordinance <hi>in</hi> a place give that name <hi>to</hi> a place. But what if he ſhould take away the Vineyard from us for our want of render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the fruit of it? Why then call them <hi>Ichabod,</hi> for the Glory is departed from Iſrael. The Glory of the Lord ſeems to be ſtanding at the Threſhold of the door. To look upon God and ſee him <hi>going,</hi> upon Ordinances and ſee them <hi>going</hi> is a moſt awful ſight, for when they go the true glory of a place goes, nor will our other good things ſtay behind, as woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience does abundantly teſtifie. If we come to loſe God's Houſe and the glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40711:57"/>
of the ſame we ſhall be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> miſerable people under Heaven: As none hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been ſo priviledged, ſo none will be ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as our ſelves.</p>
            <p>It ſorely aggravated <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s miſery i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the day of her Affliction <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 7. tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Enemy mockt at her Sabbaths, and for ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> making a mock of Sabbaths (which we do while we make a light matter of them, under-value &amp; get no good by them) God may juſtly leave the <hi>Adverſary</hi> to mock at our Sabbaths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Surely the Lord hath been long threatening, but now he is in the way of Execution it's high time for us to awake, and awaken one another.</p>
            <p>And if it will be ſo <hi>bitter to remember the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> things of God's houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they be <hi>loſt,</hi> is it not better to conſider them, love, prize<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and improve them while they are <hi>preſem?</hi> which they that do rightly ſhall never have that Occaſion to remember them when they are gone.</p>
            <p>God doth not eaſily give up, or depart from a people that he hath once viſibly and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally owned, no altho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he may obſerve a great deal of ſin and backſliding among them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. 8, 9. Where he has once built his Houſe God delights to dwell, and is not for removing till there be no other remedy 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 15, 16, 17. But if they either Idolize the Houſe of God, (as Iſrael did the Ark 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.) and grow
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40711:58"/>
ſecure and wanton by reaſon of it, as they did <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 8,—12. or do not prize it as they ought, nor make ſuch Returns as may be expected, but contrariwiſe profane and pollute it; Then <hi>Goe to my place at Shilo</hi> and ſee what I did to them, and ſo will I doe to you.</p>
            <p>To be deeply humbled <hi>for,</hi> and haſten to the bloud of ſprinkling for pardon and cleanſing <hi>of</hi> theſe provoking Evils that have been and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e among us, and to get an up-raiſed Eſteem <hi>of</hi> &amp; Affection <hi>to</hi> the Houſe of God is the only way in which we may hopefully and comfortably meet the Lord while he is yet in the way.</p>
            <p>To conlude—</p>
            <p>If one day in God's Houſe here upon Earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo much worth, what is a day, yea the <hi>DATES</hi> of <hi>ETERNITY</hi> worth in that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Houſe, that Preſence-Chamber, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Father's Houſe, where the Lord will exhibit all his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>before</hi> and ſolace himſelf <hi>with</hi> his Children for ever! Think what a ſweet time that will be. If <hi>now and then</hi> a Glimpſe of his Glory be ſo takeing and raviſhing, what will near, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, familiar, uninterrupted &amp; endleſs Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Father and Son be! If they be bleſt that may dwell in <hi>this</hi> Houſe, and ſhould ſtill praiſe him for the ſame, how will they be bleſt that ſhall for ever dwell in <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Houſe? and what ſoul-deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtingly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to whom the Lines ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all in that pleaſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace, when they ſhall
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40711:58"/>
be poſſeſſ'd of that goodly Heritage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> where we now are is but the Gate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Porch, the Courts belonging to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Glory, what then is the inmoſt Room, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Holy of Holies! If a day in theſe Courts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> worth a Thouſand, how many Thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Millions of dayes and years is a day, an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>there</hi> worth! If this place be ſo beautifull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Admirable, oh how Amiable is <hi>that</hi> Dwellin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> place! Surely it is good dwelling there. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſcurer Glimpſes of God's Glory in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be ſo precious and pleaſant, what will the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holding of him face to face be, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver and forever too!</p>
            <p>Oh then prize this Houſe as the Gate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that, and as the way that leads us thither, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> attend upon God therein accordingly, until <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can experience the Truth of what <hi>David</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> expreſſes. And be we well aſſured that Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will ſooner or later give every ſincere At-Attender on him here juſt cauſe to ſet his hand and Seal to this great Truth <hi>One day in thy Houſe is better than a THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:59"/>
            <head>Books printed for, and Sold by <hi>Joſeph Bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at his Shop at the Corner of the <hi>Priſon-Lane</hi> next the <hi>Exhange.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>ADiſcourſe concerning <hi>Comets,</hi> wherein the Nature of <hi>Blazing Stars</hi> is enquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by Mr. <hi>Increaſe Mather.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—An <hi>Eſſay</hi> for the Recording <hi>Illuſtrious Providences.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—The <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Divine <hi>Providences</hi> open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Applied. To which is Annexed</item>
               <item>A Sermon wherein is ſhewed That it is the <hi>Duty</hi> and ſhould be the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re</hi> of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lievers</hi> on Chriſt to live in the conſtant Exerciſe of <hi>Grace.</hi> by Mr. <hi>Nathana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Mather,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Self-Employment in S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cret,</hi> containing Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences upon <hi>Self-examination,</hi> Thoughts upon <hi>Painful Afflictions,</hi> Memorials for <hi>Practice.</hi> by Mr. <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is intended for the Preſs a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> Concerning the Perſon, Offices, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Jeſus Chriſt; being Sacramental Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on Chriſt by the Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Increaſe Mather.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40711:60"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
